<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Book I, Question 9</title>
        <author>Peter Gracilis</author>
        <editor>Jeffrey C. Witt</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Book I, Question 9</title>
          <date when="2017-10-10">October 10, 2017</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 License</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="L" n="lon">London, British Museum Royal 10 A I</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-critical-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 
          guidelines for a critical edition.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2015-11-20" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>File Started for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="include-list">
        <xi:include href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-lists/master/workscited.xml" xpointer="worksCited"/>
        <xi:include href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-lists/master/Prosopography.xml" xpointer="prosopography"/>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#L" n="33-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="pg-b1q9">
        <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e95">Book I, Question 9</head>
        <div xml:id="pg-b1q9-Dd1e98">
          <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e100">Concerning the text</head>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e83">
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e107" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c1-d1e3476">Nunc de veritate sive proprietate</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c1-d1e3476">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 8, c. 1 [n.1], (I, 95, ll. 4).</ref></bibl>
            </cit> 
            etc. 
            This is distinction 8. 
            To the preceding it is continued thus 
            because after the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> showed 
            that in the divine there is true generation, 
            now in this distinction he puts a multitude of properties 
            signifying its perfection.
            Et this is divided into three parts 
            because in the first place the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> 
            makes determinations about the eternal being of God, 
            in the second place about his unchangeability, 
            in the third place about his simplicity. 
            The second begins at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e134" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c2-d1e3477"><sic>deus <!-- actual Lombard text has "dei" --></sic> in solius essentia</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c2-d1e3477">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 8, c. 2 [n.1], (I, 97, ll.2).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>,
            the third at
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e149" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c3-d1e3475">eademque</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c3-d1e3475">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 8, c. 3 [n.1], (I, 98, ll. 20).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>. 
            The first is in three parts, 
            for in the first place he shows how this name <mentioned>being</mentioned> or <mentioned>essence</mentioned> 
            is proper to God, 
            in the second place from what has been said 
            is introduces a doubt, 
            and in the third place he responds to it. 
            The second begins at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e167" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c1-d1e3533">hic diligenter</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c1-d1e3533">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 8, c. 1 [n.4], (I, 95, ll. 21-22).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>.
            The third begins at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e177" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c1-d1e3586">illud ergo quod</quote>
              <bibl><ref type="commentary" target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c1-d1e3586">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 8, c. 1 [n.6], (I, 96, ll. 20).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>.
            The second principal part is undivided, 
            but the third is divided into two parts
            because in the first place 
            the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> shows the simplicity of the divine nature 
            through comparison and external relations, 
            in the second place through internal relation. 
            The second begins at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e197" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c5-d1e3477">hic diligenter</quote>
              <bibl>
                <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c5-d1e3477">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 8, c. 5 [n.1], (XXX).</ref></bibl>
              </bibl>
            </cit>.
            And this is the division of the present distinction.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="pg-b1q9-Dd1e222">
          <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e224">Question</head>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e143">
            Whether the first cause of a producibile being alone is simple,
            necessary, 
            and unchangeable or invariable?
          </p>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q9-Dd1e240">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e242">Rationes principales</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-qnasne">
              That not, there is some creature that is indivisibly simple, 
              therefore etc. 
              The antecedent is proved then because 
              to every specific grade of some thing 
              there corresponds a punctual or indivisible being. 
              This is clear because, whenever something grade is added or subtracted 
              no matter how small, the thing does not remain in the same species,
              therefore such a thing is indivisible.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-sacsne">
              <pb ed="#L" n="33-v"/>
              In the second place, 
              there something below the first cause that is necessary, 
              therefore. 
              The antecedent is clear because through
              <ref>
                <name ref="#Aquinas">the Holy Doctor</name> 
                <title ref="#SummaContraGentiles">Contra Gentiles</title>, 
                book two, chapter 29
              </ref>,
              where from what has been said 
              <cit>
                <quote>
                  therefore that in which there is not matter, 
                  or, if there is, there is not potentaility for another form, 
                  does not have the potency for non being, 
                  therefore such things are absolutely necessary
                </quote>
                <bibl>Aquinas, <title>Summa contra gentiles</title>, II, c. 29 (13, 335).</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              But it is certain that an neither an angel nor a a soul has matter, 
              therefore.
              This is confirmed 
              because an angel and a soul do not have within them 
              a principle leading them to non being, 
              therefore they have no potency for non being, 
              therefore they are necessary.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e217">
              In the third place,
              in the first cause there is an absolute modal distinction 
              and a conceptual or virtual distinction, 
              therefore.
              The antecedent for the first part is from 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#JamesViterbo">James of Viterbo</name></ref>
                <bibl>Iacobus de Viterbo, XXX</bibl>
              </cit> 
              and for the second part is from
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#AlphonsusVargas">Alphonsus</name>, distinction eight of book one, article two, conclusion four</ref>
                <bibl>Alphonsus Toletanus Vargas, I, d. 8, a. 1, conc. 4</bibl>
              </cit>.
              The consequences is clear because any such distinction is repugnant to the highest simplicity.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e235">
              In opposition is the opinion of the 
              <cit>
                <ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pl-l1d8c3"><!-- http://scta.info/resource/pl-l1d8c6" should be added when build script is capable of tokenizing these --><name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> in this distinction</ref>
                <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pl-l1d8c3">Lombardus, Sent. I, d.8, c. 3 (I, 98)</ref> et <ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pl-l1d8c6">6, (I, 100).</ref></bibl>
              </cit>.
              Again the
              <ref>
                <name ref="#Paul">Apostle</name> in <title ref="#Itim">I Timothy</title> 6
              </ref> 
              says says that
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e318" ana="#Itim6_16">
                  God alone has immortality</quote>
                <bibl>I Timotheum 6:16</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              Again <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> III <title ref="#deTrinitate">De Trinitate</title></ref> 
              says
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e334" source="http://scta.info/resource/adt-l3">
                  God alone does not change and is not able to change</quote>
                <bibl>Augustinus, De Trinitate, III, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q9-Dd1e343">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e345">First conclusion</head> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e273">
              The first conclusion: 
              it is as necessary that the first cause is 
              as it is that a creature is able to be.
              This is proved because 
              inasmuch as it is necessary that God is God and is omnipotent, 
              by as much necessity he is externally productive, 
              and by as much necessity is something external able to be produced 
              and is able to have being, 
              therefore etc.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e314">
              This is confirmed because, 
              if the first cause were not able to produce anything outside itself, 
              it would seem that from the fact that something is producible it would be produced, 
              but this is impossible. 
              Nor does this seem to be a problem 
              because it would still be able to corrupt this whole 
              and then recreate it, 
              therefore.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e322">
              First corollary: 
              thought it is not the case that a creature is not able not to be, 
              nevertheless if the first cause 
              were to act outside itself through the mode of nature, 
              then it would be necessary for some producible thing to be.
              The first part is clear 
              because some created thing is contingently produced by 
              and in conserved in its being. 
              The second part is clear 
              because, 
              if one thing were produced and not another thing, 
              then either this would be because 
              it would were determined that this thing be produced
              and not the other, 
              and not this because this is to produce freely 
              since one is equally as possible as the other,
              or this would be because one thing would be able to be produced and not the other, 
              but this is not the case because then it would be producible and not producibile. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e345">
              Second corollary: 
              if the first cause were to act outside itself 
              necessarily and naturally, all producibile and corruptibile things 
              would be produced and corrupted at the same time and equally. 
              This is clear because if <c>a</c> fire itself were able to 
              produce <c>b</c> heat and corrupt <c>b</c> heat, 
              it would produce and corrupt at the same time. 
              Therefore, 
              since the first cause alone is able with another <!-- need translation help here -->
              it is able in the genus of an efficient cause, 
              the proposed follows that if it were to act naturally, etc.
              
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e370">
              Third corollary: 
              it is not stand that the first cause is productive 
              of every producible creature 
              and to this to act outside of itself from the necessity of nature. 
              This is clear to this that to produce naturally, 
              it would follows that all producible things are produced and corrupted at the same time and equally. 
              But this implies a contradiction, therefore. 
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q9-Dd1e377">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e379">Second conclusion</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e378">
              The second conclusion: though only three supposites 
              are distinguished in the one super simple essence, 
              nevertheless this is not properly called diversity or difference.
              The first part is clear through faith because
              there is one Father, another Son, and another Holy Spirit, 
              therefore only three supposites are distinguished in the divine essence. 
              This is confirmed 
              because a distinction or difference is nothing, 
              therefore the should not be put in God. 
              This is clear because whatever is in God is something. 
              The antecedent is clear 
              because if only God and man were to exists and nothing else, 
              God and man would still be different, 
              therefore distinction or difference are nothing something or somethings. 
              For this  
              <pb ed="#L" n="34-r"/>
              conclusion there is the reasoning 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> VI <title ref="#deTrinitate">De Trinitate</title>, chapter 4, de magnis<!-- translation--></ref>
                <bibl>Augustinus, De Trinitate, VI, c. 4</bibl>
              </cit> 
              and 
              <cit> <!-- could this be the same ref ?? -->
                <ref>chapter 14, de parvis <!-- translation ?? --></ref>
                <bibl>Augustinus, De Trinitate, VI, c. 14</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              From the second part of the conclusion, 
              it follows that though it would be said truly and properly 
              that some things are distinguished in reality, 
              and in intention, and in reason, 
              nevertheless it is not properly said that 
              this distinct is intentional, real, or of reason. 
              This is clear 
              because a distinction is nothing, 
              therefore it is not. 
              The consequence is clear 
              because what is absolutely nothing does not exists
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e425">
              First corollary: 
              every perfection 
              which God really is some perfection of God formally. 
              This is clear because, 
              if the divine perfections 
              in some mode differed or were different, 
              it would follow that the divine supposites 
              would not differ only in the divine essence.
              The consequence is clear in 
              <cit>
                <ref>the first part of the second conclusion</ref>
                <bibl>Vide supra</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e435">
              Second corollary: 
              that just among divine perfections 
              there is no formal distinction, 
              so also are a distinction of reason or modal distinction repugnant to them 
              Or thus, 
              just as it does not stand that 
              the divine perfections are distinguished formally, 
              so it is also repugnant for them 
              to be distinguished by reason or formally. 
              This is clear because 
              otherwise in them there 
              would not be the highest simplicity and indifference.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e447">
              Third corollary: 
              just as it is repugnant that there are a plurality of Gods, 
              so it is repugnant that there are a formal diversity of perfections in God. 
              This is clear because, 
              if such a plurality of formalities in God were possible, 
              it follows that there is something which is absolutely formally God which is not every God. 
              Again, it would follow that something would be 
              God really which is merely contingent, 
              but this is as repugnant as it is that there are many gods, 
              therefore. 
              The first consequence is proved 
              because if divine justice is God formally, 
              then the divine wisdom, 
              if it is formally not justice, 
              then it will not be God formally. 
              The second consequence is clear 
              because the fact that <mentioned>God wants to beatify 
              <name ref="#Peter">Peter</name></mentioned> is really God, 
              and nevertheless by positing formalities of this type 
              God is contingently.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-itcpci">
              These three corollaries seem to be from the mind of 
              <ref><name ref="#Anselm">Anselm</name>  in the <title ref="#Monologion">Monologion</title> chapter 17</ref> 
              who says 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e480">
                  whatever is said essentially about the highest essence, 
                  thus this is in one consideration essentially one. 
                  For since some man is said to be a body, rational, and man, 
                  he is not in any mode or consideration said to be three things. 
                  Thus truly the highest divine essence is in no way said in such a way that 
                  it is not this same thing according to consideration and according to another</quote>
                <bibl>Anselmus, Monologion, 17, (I, 31, ll. 25-32)</bibl>
              </cit>.
              From this these corollary seem to be clear.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q9-Dd1e494">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e496">Third conclusion</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e511">
              Third conclusion: just as the first cause alone 
              has every perfection absolutely and is including itself, 
              so also is it formally and completely lacking any kind of compositions 
              and excluding from itself. <!-- translation help needed -->
              The first part is proved because according to <name ref="#Anselm">Anselm</name> God is 
              
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e506">that which nothing greater or better is able to be thought</quote>
                <bibl>Anselmus, Proslogion 3 (I, 103, ll. 1-2)</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              The second part is because simplicity should be placed before composition
              according to 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> <title ref="#DeQuantitateAnimae">De quantitate animae</title>, chapter 12</ref>
                <bibl>Augustinus, De quantitate, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>,
              ergo, 
              But the first cause alone is of the highest simplicity. 
              This is clear indivisibility, immutability, and per se actuality 
              belong to the ratio of simplicity, 
              but these things suit God alone 
              and are not able to be found in a creature.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e539">
              The first corollary: 
              any species either of a given or giveable form are perfectly 
              confluibile <!-- translation help --> into a superior form or species. 
              This is clear because no such species is unchangeable in its being, 
              therefore God is able to make it that flow together in a unified way into something superior.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e549">
              The second corollary: 
              it is not the case that some individual depends on a first cause 
              and unitively contains every degree of perfection.
              This is clear because 
              then such an individual would not be able flow unitively 
              with another individual into a superior species 
              or into some more perfect individual. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e572">
              The third corollary: 
              it is not the case for some individual that it is repugnant that 
              some dependent created being is not able to be subjectively under some accident 
              and that it is repugnant that this created thing truly is able 
              to unitively contain every grade of simplicity. <!-- NEED TRANSLATION HELP -->
              This is clear because non individual of any given 
              <pb ed="#L" n="34v"/>
              or giveable species is able to be so simple 
              that it is not able to be the subject of an elicited act or 
              the subject of some habit infused by God, therefore. 
              The antecedent is clear because simplicity of this type suits God alone.
              From what has been said the affirmative part of the conclusion follows.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q9-Dd1e561">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e563">Obiectiones et Responsiones</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e600">
              Against the first conclusion and its corollaries: 
              something other than God is necessary, therefore. 
              The antecedent is proved because the divine perfection goes out to what is produced similar to itself 
              to the degree that is not repugnant to the creature. 
              But to be necessary is not repugnant to a creature, 
              therefore the divine goodness produces the creatures in this way. 
              The major premise is known. 
              The minor premise is clear because,
              if it were repugnant to the creature to be necessary, 
              then it would seem to be by virtue of the fact that it comes from another. 
              But this is not the case 
              because the Son has his being from another, 
              and nevertheless it does not have this being contingently, 
              therefore.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e632">
              In the second place, 
              if an angel or the soul were able not to be, 
              then this would be because God withdrew his influence from them.
              But this is impossible 
              because this would mean his goodness had changed, 
              therefore such things are not able to be. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e646">
              In the third place: 
              substances separated from matter 
              do not have a passive potency for privation or corruption, 
              therefore they are not able not to be. 
              The consequence holds 
              since matter is the ratio maintenance and corruption in creatures. 
              These are the arguments of <name ref="#Aquinas">the Holy Doctor</name>,
              in the place it was noted earlier at the beginning of the question.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e665">
              In the fourth place: 
              because either for something to be necessary it corresponds 
              precisely either that it is punctual or quantitive.
              If the first, then it is not of immense perfection. 
              If the second, then it is able to be imagined in this species to be more or less necessary 
              since it is possible to everything something less, 
              so it is possible to give to this necessity less quantity, 
              and thus many things will be necessary.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e706">
              In the fifth place: 
              if the entire line of producbile things were contingent with respect to being and non being, 
              it follows that the whole would be able to be put completely into being. 
              The consequent is false through what has been said 
              because the first cause would not be able to act outside itself. 
              The consequence is clear 
              because the whole is able not to be as
              <cit>
                <ref>the first corollary</ref>
                <bibl>Vide supra</bibl>
              </cit> 
              says.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e715">
              In the sixth place: 
              no individual of an inferior species 
              is able to contain the total perfection of its species, 
              therefore it is necessary that one thing is not able to contain the total breadth of necessity, 
              therefore there is not only one thing in that species.
              The antecedent is clear through the
              <cit>
                <ref>second corollary of the third conclusion</ref>
                <bibl>Vide supra</bibl>
              </cit>, 
              and the consequences are clear.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e736">
              This is confirmed 
              because <mentioned>to be</mentioned>, as the proposition
              <mentioned>man is an animal</mentioned> signified, 
              is necessary being, 
              therefore there are many necessary beings. 
              The consequence holds because this is not God..
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e756">
              Again, to this proposition nothing is, 
              a contradiction does not follow, 
              there this is able to be true, 
              therefore nothing is necessary to be necessary. 
              The consequences holds, 
              and the antecedent is proved 
              because to no negative does an affirmative follow, 
              therefore neither does some contradiction 
              because every contradiction 
              is composed from an affirmative and negative 
              or at least includes one.
              
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e791">
              Against the second conclusion: 
              in the first place it is argued 
              the authority the <ref><name ref="#JohnDamascenus">Damascene</name>, in book one, chapter three</ref>,
              where he says 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e627">
                  Whatever we say about God affirmatively 
                  does not show his nature but those things, 
                  which are about his nature. For if you say he is good, 
                  if just, and if wise, and anything else, you do not speak his nature.
                </quote>
                <bibl>Ioannes Damescenus, I, c. 4, (PG 94.799BC); Burgundionis versio 4,5, p. 21, 41-45)</bibl> <!-- quote also in Marsilius of Inghen, q. 12, p. 83,  and Rimini 1, d. 8, q. 1, p. 25-->
              </cit>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e806">
              Contra primum corollarium: si Deus esset 
              immense simplex, aut divisibiliter aut indivisibiliter. Non primum quia tunc haberet partes. 
              Nec secundum quia tunc solum per indivisibilem staret a nihilo, et sic infinite minus 
              distaret divina essentia angelo quam quaecumque creatura, quod est falsum.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e816">
              Secundo: sapientia in communi 
              non est iustitia in communi, ergo ne infinita sapientia infinita iustitia. Tenet consequentia quia infinitas 
              non tollit rationem propriam alicuius rei, ut videtur.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e825">
              Contra secundum corollarium: illa 
              quae non sunt synonyma significant diversas res vel eandem diversis rationibus, sed 
              bonitas et iustitia, misericordia et aeternitas non sunt synonyma, ideo ergo sed non 
              <pb ed="#L" n="35-r"/> 
              significant diversas res, ergo diversos modos. Ergo in Deo est distinctio modalis 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#JamesViterbo">Iacobus de Viterbio</name> <title>quodlibet</title> tertio, quaestione septima</ref>
                <bibl>Iacobus de Viterbio, Quodlibet III, q. 7, 2, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-ssqnmv">
              Secundo sequitur quod volitiva divina formaliter esset intellectiva divina 
              et econverso. Consequens est falsum quia tunc, quidquid esset obiectum, unus esset obiectum alterius modo. Hoc 
              est falsum, quia deus intelligit malum culpae quod tamen nullo modo <unclear cert="high">vult</unclear>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e849">
              Tertia: illa quae 
              necessitat intellectum ad actus distinctos essentialiter secundum rationem vel conceptibiliter distinguitur, sed 
              perfectiones divinae necessitant ad actus distinctos essentialiter intellectum, ergo huiusmodi perfectiones 
              divinae conceptibiliter seu virtualiter sunt distinctae. Maior patet ubi una res necessitat 
              ad actus distinctos essentialiter facit illud idem quod facerent 
              <app>
                <lem n="facerent"/>
                <rdg wit="#L" type="correction-deletion">
                  <del rend="strikethrough">s</del>
                </rdg>
              </app> 
              res diversae realiter distinctae. 
              Minor patet quia sapientia divina necessitat intellectum ad conceptum sapientiae et bonitas ad 
              conceptum bonitatis et tales conceptus sunt realiter et essentialiter distincti, ergo <name ref="#AlphonsusVargas">Alphonsus</name>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e892">
              Quarto contra 3m corollarium: sapientiae divinae ut sic non repugnat non iustitia, ergo sapientia 
              aliquo modo non est eadem cum iustitia, sed sapientiae divinae non repugnat simpliciter alius 
              deus, ergo.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e901">
              Contra tertiam conclusionem est propositio alia de causis qua dicitur quod intelligentia est substantia quae non 
              dividitur, ergo non solus Deus.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-pdaiei">
              Secundo 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Aristotle">Philosophus</name> II <title ref="#deAnima">De anima</title></ref>
                <bibl>Aristoteles, De anima, II, XXX</bibl>
              </cit> 
              dicit <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e4530">intellectus simpliciter est impermixtus 
              et immaterialis</quote>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e918">
              Tertio, contra <ref>primum corollarium</ref> est <ref>prima ratio in oppositum</ref>, quia quaelibet simplex est tam simplex 
              quod ei correspondet unicus gradus et esse punctuale, ergo.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e930">
              Quarto autoritate 
              <ref>
                <name ref="#Averroes">Commentatoris</name> 
                12o <title ref="#Metaphysics">Metaphysicae</title>
              </ref> dicentis quod 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e724">omnes formae 
                  <app>
                    <lem>sunt</lem>
                    <rdg wit="#L" type="correction-addition">
                      <add place="aboveLine">sunt</add>
                    </rdg>
                  </app> 
                  actu existentes in primo motore quae in potentia sunt 
                  in materia prima,</quote>
                <bibl>Averroes, XXX</bibl>
              </cit> 
              ergo in Deo non est omnimoda simplicitas.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e949">
              Ad primum, negatur antecedens. Ad probationem, 
              negatur maior et minor. Et ad probationem minoris, dico quod necesse esse repugnat creaturae non solum 
              ex eo quod est ab alio, sed quia etiam libere contingenter producitur de nihilo et contingenter conservatur.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e957">Ad secundum, conceditur assumptum et negatur quod illud sit impossibile, quia nec sequitur voluntatem divinam mutari 
              vel esse mutabilem, aliter posset probari quod necessario omne futurum eveniret.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e972">
              Ad tertium, 
              negatur consequentia, quia tunc accidentia et lumen productum in medio aliquo modo non possent non esse. 
              Secundo, dico quod licet non habeant materiam habent, tamen suum nihil quasi materiam et hoc sufficit.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e981">
              Ad 
              quartum, dici potest esse punctuale sibi correspondet et indivisibile, et negatur consequentia, ergo non 
              est immensae perfectionis, quia simul est indivisibilis super simplex et immensus non habens in 
              se formaliter latitudinem gradualem quamvis supereminenter contineat omnem perfectionis 
              latitudinem.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e999">
              Ad quintum, conceditur consequens quia quaelibet pars illius latitudinis potest poni 
              in esse, et si infertur igitur potest poni inesse tota simul. Negatur consequentia, quia sicut etiam non sequitur 
              quaelibet pars illius latitudinis potest poni inesse ergo possibile est poni inesse quamlibet eius partem, 
              sic non sequitur quaelibet pars a continui a <name ref="#Sortes">Sorte</name> potest videri, ergo <name ref="#Sortes">Sortes</name> potest videre <c>a</c> 
              continui quamlibet partem, nec sequitur quilibet gradus perfectionis possibilis potest poni inesse. Ergo possibile 
              est quod ponatur inesse quilibet gradus perfectionis possibilis, licet consequens tenuerim probabiliter 
              in 
              <cit>
                <ref>meo principio</ref>
                <bibl>Supra vide</bibl>
              </cit> 
              contra <unclear cert="medium">praedicatorem</unclear>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1027">
              Ad sextum, negatur consequentia, quia deitas non se habet per 
              modum speciei creatae personae nec divinae personae per modum individuorum, quia, licet 
              duos homines sunt aliquod unum maius quam unus solus, tamen duae personae divinae 
              non sunt maius quam una sola, ut dicit 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Augustinus</name> VIII <title ref="#deTrinitate">De Trinitate</title>, capitulo primo.</ref>
                <bibl>Augustinus, De Trinitate, VIII, c. 1 (XXX)</bibl>
              </cit>
            </p> 
            
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1045">
              Ad aliud, negatur 
              consequentia, quia conclusio et corollaria intelliguntur de entitatibus realibus et non de complexe  
              <pb ed="#L" n="35-v"/> 
              significantibus.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-aanesa">
              Ad aliam, negatur antecedens quia ad illam, sequitur necesse esse non esse necesse esse. Et 
              ad improbationem dico quod impossibile sequitur quodlibet et per consequens ex negativa sequitur affirmativa.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-apcesa">
              Ad 
              primum contra secundam conclusionem dicitur quod <name ref="#JohnDamascenus">Damascenus</name> non loquitur de perfectionibus quod non realiter sint in 
              Deo sed de nominibus quae de Deo praedicantur quorum aliqua secundum eum non praedicantur naturam, 
              sed ea quae sunt circa naturam quod non est intelligendum quantum ad rem significatum, quia si res 
              quae est sapientia divina non esset divina natura, sed aliquid circa naturam, non solum distingueretur  
              formaliter, sed realiter et simpliciter quod est falsum. Sed intelligitur quo ad modum praedicandi quia 
              talia nomina praedicantur de Deo denominative, et quae sic praesentatur de Deo quantum ad 
              modum praedicandi non dicunt naturam, sed aliquid circa naturam. Haec est solutio <name ref="#AlphonsusVargas">Alphonsi</name>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1101">
              Ad secundum, primo posset dici quod divisibiliter seu per divisibile distat angelo quia distat 
              per totam perfectionem omnium creaturarum actualium et possibilium. Et negatur consequentia igitur <unclear cert="low">partes</unclear> 
              quia illa divisibilitas non est deo intrinseca sed extrinseca.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1110">
              Secundo posset dici hanc negando 
              consequentiam distat indivisibiliter, ergo infinite minus quam quaecumque circa quia illud indivisibile per 
              quid distat est immensum quia est Deus.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1118">
              Ad aliud, negatur consequentia. Ratio <supplied>est</supplied> quia sapientia infinita 
              et bonitas infinita in re sunt aliquid circumscripta omni ratione intellectus sapientia vero in communi 
              et bonitas in communi non sic quia non sunt nisi quidam conceptus vel entia rationis. Et ad 
              probationem quia infinitas non tollit rationem formalem alicuius conceditur, sed hoc non probat intentum, 
              quia sapientia et bonitas in communi non solum praedicantur de sapientia et bonitate infinita, sed 
              etiam de finita. De hoc vide <name ref="#AlphonsusVargas">Alphonsum</name>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1143">
              Ad aliud contra tertium corollarium, concesso antecedente, 
              negatur consequentia, nam non sequitur haec res diversimodae est quia possibile est quod propositum idem significatum 
              una sit vera et alia falsa, non tamen sequitur quod significatum sit verum et falsum.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1151">
              Ad aliud, 
              conceditur consequens. Et ad improbationem, <mentioned>quia tunc obiectum unius,</mentioned> etc., conceditur. Et cum improbatur, <mentioned>quia Deus intelligit 
              malum</mentioned> etc., conceditur, sed non sequitur quod infertur.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1160">
              Secundo dico quod voluntas divina intelligit omnem 
              malum quia intellectus divinus qui intelligit est formaliter voluntas divina, malum ergo 
              est obiectum voluntatis, non ut volitum, sed ut cognitum et intellectum.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1168">
              Tertio posset negari illa 
              consequentia, voluntas divina et intellectus sunt idem, igitur quidquid intellectus intelligit voluntas vult.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1174">
              Ad aliud, negatur maior et minor quia non oportet quod omnem illud quod necessitat ad conceptus 
              distinctos sit conceptibiliter distinctum nisi velimus ab uti vocabulo, nec etiam perfectio 
              divina necessitat ad distinctionem actuum diversorum ut assumit ratio.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1195">
              Ad rationem 
              contra tertium corollarium, negatur maior quia sapientia divina est omnis perfectio formaliter, et omne quod 
              est melius esse quam non esse simpliciter sub bono intellectu.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1203">
              Ad primam auctoritatem contra 
              tertiam conclusionem, intelligentia est substantia quae non dividitur. Hoc est verum quantum ad partes naturae vel 
              quantum ad durationem, quae est tota simul.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1211">
              Ad aliam, dicitur quod intellectus est virtus simplex, 
              id est, non organica. Hoc voluit <name ref="#Aristotle">Philosophus</name>. Secundo dicitur simplex aliquo modo non simpliciter quia omnis creatura 
              aliquo modo est composita et potentialitati subiecta.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1225">
              Ad prima rationem in oppositum dicitur quod si antecedens 
              intelligitur de simpliciter simplici est falsum. Et ad probationem dicitur quod non valet consequentia. Et si ultra inferretur 
              anima non est simplex, igitur habet partes, consequentia negatur.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1233">
              Ad aliud dicitur huiusmodi formas 
              in primo motore esse in distinctas actu quia creatura in Deo non est aliud quam divina natura 
              <pb ed="#L" n="36-r"/>
              penitus in distincta.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-aarspd">Ad alias rationes in oppositum patet solutio per dictam</p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="pg-b1q9-Dd1e884">
          <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e886">
            <supplied>Conclusiones pro distinctione octava</supplied>
          </head>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1250">
            Nunc de veritate seu proprietate, haec distinctio continet nona conclusiones. Prima quod solus Deus 
            vere et proprie est quia eius essentia non novit praeteritum vel futurum. Hoc est non <unclear cert="low">subest</unclear> 
            praeteritioni aut futuritioni, sicut cetera creata
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1264">Secunda conclusio: ideo dicit Deus semper fuit vel erit, 
            ut intelligatur quod non incepit esse nec desinet.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1270">
            Tertia conclusio: quod licet verba substantiva 
            diversorum temporum dicantur de deo, scilicet fuit, erit, est, et erat, non 
            tamen de Deo dicuntur quia esse divinum praeteritioni aut
            <app>
              <lem n="aut"/>
              <rdg wit="#L" type="correction-deletion">
                <del rend="strikethrough">subiectio</del>
              </rdg>
            </app> 
            futuritioni subiaceat 
            cum temporalis motus Deo repugnet, sed dicuntur ad denotandum Deum esse 
            aeternitatem et permanentiae ipsius proprietatem.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1286">
            Quarta conclusio: solius Dei essentia incommutabilis 
            proprie dicitur quia nec mutatur nec mutari potest, omnis autem creatura mutari potest, Deus 
            autem non nec loco nec tempore nec affectione, et ita sine sui mutatione cunctas condidit 
            creaturas. Et per consequens solus Deus proprie habet immortalitatem, omnis autem creatura est mortalis 
            ex sua natura, quia sua mutatio mors appellatur.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1299">
            Quinta conclusio: Deus solus est vere ac 
            proprie simplex, quia in eo nec partium nec accidentium sive formarum est diversitas vel vario 
            modo sive multitudo. Omnis creatura est multiplex, quamvis spiritualis creatura respectu corporalis 
            dicitur simplex, non tamen est vere simplex, quia in tali est diversitas accidentium sive formarum 
            accidentalium, ut in animalibus humanis et angelis, nullum enim quod est vere simplex est mutabile.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1311">
            Sexta conclusio quod anima respectu corporis simplex dicitur quia <unclear cert="medium">molae</unclear> non diffunditur per 
            <app>
              <lem type="conjecture-supplied"><supplied>spatium</supplied></lem>
              <rdg wit="#L">saptium</rdg>
            </app> 
            loci, sed in uno quoque corpore est in toto tota et in qualibet eius parte tota.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1318">
            Septima conclusio: quod licet 
            Deus dicatur multipliciter, scilicet bonus iustus sapiens et magnus, tamen hoc non est 
            propter diversitatem accidentium, sed propter multitudinem nominum quae, licet multa sint et diversa, 
            unum tamen significant, scilicet naturam divinam.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1328">
            Octava conclusio: quod proprie Deus non dicitur substantia quasi sit 
            subiectum suae bonitatis vel alicuius accidentis, sicut substantia corporalis, quae ideo dicitur substantia 
            quia subsistit et est multorum accidentium subiectum, sed Deus proprie et vere dicitur essentia.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1336">
            Nona conclusio: Deus, ideo simplex dicitur quia ipse est quidquid habet excepto quod persona dicitur relative 
            ad alteram, nec tamen una est altera, nam Pater habet Filium ad quem relative dicitur, et 
            tamen Pater non est Filius, et Filius habet Patrem, nec tamen est Pater in quo vero ad semet ipsum 
            dicitur non ad alteram, hoc est quod habet. Unde ipse Deus est unus et habet vitam et est ipse 
            una vita nec aliud est habens et aliud quod habetur, sicut in ceteris rebus ubi semper sequitur aliqua distinctio.
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>  
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>