<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Book I, Question 5</title>
        <author>Peter Gracilis</author>
        <editor>Jeffrey C. Witt</editor>
        <editor>John T. Slotemaker</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Book I, Question 5</title>
          <date when="2017-08-11">August 08, 2017</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-SA 4.0)</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="L" n="lon">London, British Museum Royal 10 A I</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-critical-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 
          guidelines for a translated edition.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2014-06-16" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>File Started for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="include-list">
        <xi:include href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-lists/master/workscited.xml" xpointer="worksCited"/>
        <xi:include href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-lists/master/Prosopography.xml" xpointer="prosopography"/>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#L" n="24-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="pg-b1q5">
        <head xml:id="pg-b1q5-Hd1e3724">Question 5</head>
        <div xml:id="pg-b1q5-Dd1e3727">
          <head xml:id="pg-b1q5-Hd1e3729">
            <supplied>Regarding the Text</supplied>
          </head>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e283">
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q5-Qd1e3737" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d4c1-d1e3476">Hic oritur quaestio</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d4c1-d1e3476">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 4, c. 1, [n.1], (I, 77, ll. 22-23).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>.
            This is the fourth distinction, which continues the preceding 
            because, after the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> determined about the unity of the essence 
            and the trinity of persons, then in this part he determines about their origin and their difference. 
            And it is divided into four parts according to which the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> does four things.
            In the first place he introduces the question, 
            in the second place he argues through reason, 
            in the third place responds to a doubt, 
            and in the fourth place he puts the solution of the argument. 
            The second begins at  
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q5-Qd1e3758" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d4c1-d1e3476">si enim Deus genuit Deum</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d4c1-d1e3476">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 4, c. 1, [n.1], (I, 77, ll. 24).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>. 
            The third at
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q5-Qd1e3767" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d4c1-d1e3481">ad quod respondentes dicimus</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d4c1-d1e3481">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 4, c. 1, [n.1/2], (I, 78, ll. 3).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>.
            The fourth at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q5-Qd1e3776" source=" http://scta.info/resource/pll1d4c2-d1e3535">nunc ad praemissam 
              dubitationem seu quaestionem</quote>
              <!-- bibl still needs paragraph, page and line numbers from most recent brady edition -->
              <bibl><ref target=" http://scta.info/resource/pll1d4c2-d1e3535">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 4, c. 2, [n. 5], (XXX).</ref></bibl> 
            </cit>.
            And this is the division of the distinction in general.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="pg-b1q5-Dd1e3785">
          <head xml:id="pg-b1q5-Hd1e3787">
            <supplied>Question: whether God eternally generated God before he produced a dependent bodily being?</supplied>
          </head>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e310">Whether God eternally generated God before he produced a dependent bodily being?
          </p>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q5-Dd1e3791">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q5-Hd1e3793">
              <supplied>Principal arguments</supplied>
            </head>
            <!-- add new paragraph here in image coordinates-->
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-qnqdie">
              That not because God did not generate God, therefore. 
              The consequence is clear, 
              and the antecedent is proved because God did not generate another God different from himself, 
              therefore he did not generate God.
              The consequence holds because <unclear>nothing</unclear> <!-- ms seems to have "nihil" but the sense is unclear --> is able to generate itself nor another 
              because then there would be many gods, therefore etc. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-ssaidi">
              In the second place, if he generated a God different than himself, it follows that 
              there would be some reason signaling why one would generate another distinct from itself rather than the other.
              The consequent is false because there is no such 
              reason discoverable of giveable for one that does not equally apply to the other, 
              even in the case of an infinity of things.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-tfiqef">
              In the third place, the Son in the divine began to be, therefore hew was not before etc.
              The consequence holds and the antecedent is proved because 
              the Son is in some instant and was never before that instant, 
              therefore in this instant he began to be. This is confirmed because the Son 
              began to be in some instant because, if did not begin to be etc., 
              it follows that he did not begin to be in this instant, which is false.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e375">
              In opposition is 
              <cit>
                <ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d4c1-d1e3481">
                  the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> in this distinction
                </ref>
                <bibl>
                  <ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d4c1-d1e3481">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 4, c. 1, [n.2], (I, 78, ll. 15-33).</ref>
                </bibl>
              </cit>
              because 
              <ref corresp="#pg-b1q5-Qd1e3830">
                <name ref="#Athanasius">Athansius</name> in <title>Symbolo</title>
              </ref> 
              says
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q5-Qd1e3830">eternal Father eternal Son</quote>
                <bibl>Symbolum S. Athansii</bibl>
              </cit> 
              etc.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q5-Dd1e3842">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q5-Hd1e3844"><supplied>First conclusion</supplied></head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e391">
              First conclusion: though <name ref="#Mary">the Virgin Maria</name> 
              conceived the same son temporally 
              which God the Father generated eternally, 
              nevertheless the <name ref="#Mary">Virgin Mother</name> conceived something 
              that God the Father did not generate.
              The first is clear because the son of God the Father and of the 
              <name ref="#Mary">Virgin Mary</name> is the same thing. 
              The second is clear because the <name ref="#Mary">Virgin</name> conceived the body of Christ 
              and God the Father did not generate this.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e403">
              The first corollary: though Christ was eternally, nevertheless he temporally 
              <pb ed="#L" n="24-v"/> 
              began to be Christ.
              The first part is clear because the Son was eternally. 
              The second part is clear because he began to be man temporally,
              therefore he temporally began to be Christ. 
              The consequence holds because, just as the rational soul
              and the body are one man, so God and man are one Christ.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e414">
              The second corollary: though there was some man eternally, 
              nevertheless whatever is a man came to be a man temporally.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e420">
              Third corollary: 
              this demonstration does not follow, <mentioned>he was in Christ eteranlly, 
              therefore he did not begin to be man temporally</mentioned>. 
              This is clear from the same means <!-- need better translatin for "medio" --> 
              because the humanity of Christ began to be temporally.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e430">
              Another corollary: though Christ is necessarily as much the Son, as he is God, 
              nevertheless Christ is contingently the son of someone. 
              The first is clear because as the Father is necessarily the Father, so
              the Son is necessarily the Son and both are God. 
              The second is clear because he is contingently the son of the <name ref="#Mary">Virgin</name>.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q5-Dd1e3882">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q5-Hd1e3884"><supplied>Secunda conclusio</supplied></head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e438">
              Second conclusion: though with respect to us 
              it is not evidently probable that ther eare not many sons in the divine, 
              nevertheless it is necessary that God the Father begets a single Son 
              coeternal and consubstantial with himself.
              The first is clear because every means
              evident to us for inferring that <mentioned>the father generates one son</mentioned> is able to 
              infer equally <mentioned>the Son produces another Son</mentioned> 
              because all three persons are of the same perfection, 
              omnipotence, and activity. 
              The second is clear in the present distinction.
              Again, it is clear through 
              <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Augusine</name> in book VI <title ref="#deTrinitate">De Trinitate</title>, in the secon chapter</ref>, 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q5-Qd1e3906">the Son is God from God but not except through generation</quote>
                <bibl>Augustinus, De Trinitate VI, 2 (PL ??)</bibl>
              </cit>, 
              therefore etc. 
              This is confirmed because de facto God 
              the Father produced or beget only one Son equal to himself in every respect, 
              therefore it necessary that this is so. 
              The consequence is clear from what has been said above. 
              The antecedent is a catholic truth.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-pcqgpc">
              The first corollary: that it is not able to be demonstrated to us in this life 
              that there is one Son any more than it is an infinity are generated.
              The conclusion is clear.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e472">
              Second corollary: it is not evidently probable 
              that there are productions of diverse types in the divine.
              This is clear because by faith alone it is held that there are only two, 
              namely generation and spiration.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-tcsado">
              Third corollary: just as there are many necessary things 
              which are not demonstrably necessarily evident, 
              so many things are impossible 
              which even imply a contradiction to which no one is able to be led 
              through natural reason alone.
              The first part is clear from the articles of faith that are signifying the Trinity. 
              The second is clear because the statement that <mentioned>Father does not generate the Son </mentioned> 
              includes a hidden contradiction which no one in the natural light
              is able to illuminate or show demonstratively to another.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q5-Dd1e3944">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q5-Hd1e3946"><supplied>Third conclusion</supplied></head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e501">
              Third conclusion: thought God the Father eternally generated 
              God the Son, it is nevertheless not properly said that after his generation 
              he produced something temporally.
              The first is clear through what has been said 
              and it is able to be confirmed through  
              <ref><title ref="#ps">Psalm</title> 2</ref> 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q5-Qd1e3965" ana="#ps2_7">Dominus dixit ad me 
                  Filius meus est tu, ego hodie genui te</quote>
                <bibl>Psalmus 2:7</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              The second is proved because any divine act internal to itself 
              is measured in an instant of eternity, therefore terms conveying a lapse 
              or difference of time are no properly said about the divine.
              The consequence holds because <mentioned>after</mentioned>, 
              <mentioned>before</mentioned>, <mentioned>when</mentioned>, 
              and similar terms deal with differences of time. 
              The antecedent is clear through 
              <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> in <ref><title ref="#ps">Psalm</title> 101</ref> 
              where he says: 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q5-Qd1e3999">Aeternitas ipsa dei substantia 
                  est, quae nihil habet mutabile; ibi nihil est praeteritum quasi <sic>iam <!-- dbcheck --></sic> non sit, nihil est futurum quasi 
                  nondum sit; non est ibi, nisi est; non est ibi, fuit vel erit</quote>
                <bibl>Augustine, Commentary on Ps. 25 <!-- db check --></bibl>
              </cit>.
              Again, 
              Item, <ref>the same author in book XII <title ref="#CityOfGod">De 
                civitate <supplied>Dei</supplied></title>, in chapter 15</ref>: 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q5-Qd1e4023">Istae divisiones seu dimensiones temporalium spatiorum quae 
                  usitate et proprie dicuntur <unclear>tempora</unclear> a motu siderum ceperunt unde etiam Deus, cum instituit, 
                  dixit: 
                  <mentioned>Et sint in signa et tempora et dies et annos</mentioned>
                </quote>
                <bibl>Augustine, De civitate Dei, XII, capitulo 15</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              Again,
              <ref corresp="pg-b1q5-Qfddspe">the same author in <title ref="#deDiversisQuaestionibus">83 questions</title></ref>,
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q5-Qfddspe" type="paraphrase">Filius Dei debet 
                dici natus, quia semper nascitur, quia eius nativitas seu generatio numquam praeteriit, 
                sed semper praesens est
                </quote>
                <bibl>Augustinus, De diversis quaestionibus octoginta tribus, q.37 (CCSL 44A, 59, ll. 6-7).</bibl>
                <note>Note that Gracilis explicitly identifies this quotation as rough paraphrase. See his note that immedieately follows.</note>
              </cit>. 
              See the text because these words are not the precise words. 
              Nevertheless not that there it is not always taken for a temporal difference, 
              but for an eternal measure or instant.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e579">
              The first corollary: though God the Father before the creation of things 
              did not generate his son, 
              nevertheless no
              <pb ed="#L" n="25-r"/>
              created thing was coeternal with him. 
              The first is clear like the conclusion because, just as there is not after in eternity, 
              so there is not before. 
              The second is clear because otherwise God would not have produced from the beginning of time, 
              which is false because God created etc.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e605">
              The second corollary: in some sign or instant the Father generates 
              and he never generates before that moment. 
              And nevertheless the Father does not begin to generate because the Father 
              generates in an instant of eternity 
              and never before that moment because before that moment there was not instant.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e619">
              Third corollary: though the Father in some 
              instant generates the son and will never generate him after that moment, 
              nevertheless he will not cease to generate and does not cease.
              This is clear from nature <!-- took some liberty here with translation of fundamento --> 
              of the instant of eternity because after that instant 
              nothing is or will be. 
              From these things the negative part of the title is clear, 
              namely that before corporeal being was made temporally made 
              God generated God the Son eternally. 
              This is clear when taking <mentioned>before</mentioned> in the matter stated.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q5-Dd1e4068">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q5-Hd1e4070"><supplied>Objections and responses</supplied></head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e633">
              Against the first conclusion: in the divine there is no motion, 
              therefore there is no generation.
              The consequence holds because every motion 
              is a generation. The antecedent is clear 
              <cit>
                <ref>in first book of <title ref="#iac">James</title></ref>
                <bibl>Iacobus 1:? <!-- could be a cryptic james of viterbo reference --></bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e644">
              In the second place, 
              the <name ref="#Mary">Virgin</name> did not 
              beget anything except a creature, but the Son of God is not a creature, 
              therefore etc.
              The major premise is from 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name>, <title ref="#Enchiridion">Enchiridion</title>, chapter 34</ref>
                <bibl>Augustinus, Enchiridion, 34 (PL ??)</bibl>
              </cit> 
              The minor is clear
              <cit>
                <ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pl-l3d2">in book 3 of the <title ref="#Sentences">Sentences</title>, distinction 11</ref>
                <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pl-l3d2">Lombard, Sententia, III, d. 2 (II, 27-31) <!-- dbcheck this is might need to be distinction 11 -->.</ref></bibl>
              </cit>.
              Again, the argument made before the opposition is against this conclusion.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e665">
              In the third place against its corollaries, 
              some act of understanding of the Father precedes the act of generating, 
              therefore the Son was not etenrally. The consequence is clear because the Father was knowing 
              not only in the Son, but also in himself as is clear through
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> III <title ref="#deTrinitate">De Trinitate</title></ref>
                <bibl>Augustinus, De Trinitate, III, ?? (PL ??)</bibl>
              </cit>.
              Therefore it seems that the Father had the knowledge of 
              understanding before the expression of the word.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e685">
              Against the second conclusion is 
              <cit>
                <ref>the second argument made in the opposing arguments</ref>
                <bibl>Vide supra <!-- second principle argument --></bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e689">
              In the second place, 
              if God generates God, 
              therefore he either generates with wisdom or without wisdom. 
              If the first, then the same thing is the terminus from which it was produced 
              and the terminus to which it was produced, which does not seem to be true. 
              If without wisdom, then the Father produces the Son in ingorance, 
              which is false.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e699">
              Against the third conclusion is  
              <cit>
                <ref>the third argument in the opposition</ref>
                <bibl>Vide supra <!-- third principle argument --></bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e703">
              In the second place, every ratio different from the being in God 
              is posterior to the being itself. However to generate the Son 
              is a denomination or ratio different from the being of God, therefore it is posterior. 
              Therefore it is both prior and posterior. 
              The major premise is proved because in the divine essence there is an order of essential reasons
              according to  
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Dionysius">Dionysius</name>, <title ref="#deDivinisNominibus">De divinis nominibus</title>, chapter 3</ref>
                <bibl>Pseudo-Dionysius, De divinis nominibus, c. 3 (PG ??)</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              Again, it seems that God is living prior to understanding, 
              and understanding prior to willing. But these by nature
              precede the generation of the Son, therefore.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e725">
              In the third place, that which has the ratio of the beginning in some way precedes what it begins. 
              But the Father with respect to the Son and the understanding of the Father with respect to the 
              his speaking has the ratio of the beginning, therefore in some way he precedes
              This is confirmed because to understand is common to the three suposites but to speak, 
              therefore understanding is prior to speaking. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e740">
              To the first: the consequence is denied. 
              With respect to the proof I say that not every generation is motion, just as is clear from this.
              In the second place, it is said according to 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#JamesViterbo">James of Viterbo</name>, in the second question of <title>de Divinis Praedicamentis</title></ref>
                <bibl>Iacobus de Viterbo</bibl>
              </cit> 
              that sometimes a genus indicates an imperfection 
              and a species indicates a perfection, 
              and in such a case the genus is not said about God but the species is appropriately said about God, 
              just as it is clear in the proposed about generation and motion. 
              Sometimes it the converse, 
              and in such a case the genus is said about God but the species is not, 
              just as the universal whole is said about God 
              and the integral whole is not because God does not have parts.
              Sometimes bot the genus and species speak a perfection and then each is suitable to God. 
              For this it is clear that, granted there is motion superior to generation and the genus, 
              it nevertheless does not follow that since generation is said of God, 
              therefore this is also true of motion.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e768">
              To the second it is said that 
              <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name>
              wishes to says that the <name ref="#Mary">Virgin</name> did 
              not beget anything except Christ, who according to his humanity is called a creature, 
              as 
              genuit nisi Christum, qui secundum humanitatem potest dici creatura, ut dicit 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Lombard">Lombard</name> says in distinction 11 of the book III</ref>
                <bibl>Lombardus, Sent. III, d. 11, c. 2, [n.4], (II, 79, ll. 25-26).</bibl>
              </cit>.
              This is addressed in a different way in the following.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e784">
              To the third: the antecedent is denied. 
              With respect to the proof it is said that 
              the knowledge of the Father in himself is not prior to the knowledge of the Son, 
              indeed they are essentially the same. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e790">
              To the first argument in the opposition: the antecedent is denied, 
              and with respect to the proof the consequence is denied 
              because, though God does not generate another God, 
              nevertheless he generates God the Son, 
              who is different in personhood, but is nevertheless not another God.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-apcess">
              To the first argument against the second conclusion, which is the second argument 
              in the opposition,  
              <ref>
                <name ref="#HugolinoOfOrvieto">Hugolinus</name>
              </ref>
              would say:
              <pb ed="#L" n="25-v"/> 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q5-Qd1e4301">
                  I concede the consequence, while assigning the ratio of it 
                  to this. that the Father produces the entire breadth of his cognition into being 
                  by saying one word. Therefore therefore there are not many words nor many sons
                </quote>
                <bibl>Hugolinus de Urbi Veteri, ??</bibl>
              </cit>.
              But this does not seem to be a sufficient reason because 
              could still be objected, why through this total immense breadth of cognition
              did he produce this Son and not a different one. 
              In the second place 
              <ref><name ref="#JohannesBrakel">Brinkel</name></ref> 
              would say to this that 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q5-Qd1e4317">he produced this Son and not another 
                  because in God there is only this productive memory and there it is not possible for there to be another.</quote>
                <bibl>Johannes Brinkel, ?? <!--check for correct spelling and correct unique ID --></bibl>
              </cit>.
              But this is similarly not sufficient because it would thus be possible to say 
              anything about any man becuase in him there is only one productive memory
              and nevertheless he has many words. 
              Again he solves the same through the same and thus does not return an argument, 
              since memory, intelligence, and cognition are in the Son just as in the Father. 
              Therefore I say otherwise that no argument is known to us for why the Father generated this Son and not another, 
              an argument in which the antecedent is known to us from the consequent can be inferred because, 
              given any such reason, 
              it is equally able to be inferred about the Son and the Holy Spirit.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e855">
              To the second it is said that he generated with wisdom to good sense,
              ad for the disproof the consequence is denied.
              Again, it is said that, if the same thing is taken essentially, 
              the consequent is conceded. If personally, then the consequence is denied.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e862">
              To the third it is said that God generated God, and here this stands for a person.
              Therefore, in the argument that just as it is conceded that there are three persons, so there are three Gods,  
              the consequence is denied because the Church does not admit that these things are equal.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e870">
              To the first argument against the third conclusion: 
              the antecedent is denied, and with respect to the proof 
              the consequence is denied. From this it follows that 
              this is not well or sufficiently explained. The third begins through these 
              propositions, 
              <mentioned><c>a</c> is in the present instant and never was before this</mentioned>, 
              therefore <c>a</c> begins to be, 
              But it ought to be said: 
              <mentioned><c>a</c> is in this instant of time</mentioned>, etc. 
              And thus it is able to be said about <mentioned>he ceases</mentioned> in its own unique way. 
              To the confirmation, the consequence is denied because
              he argues from the inferior to the superior with the negation placed before the part of the predicate. <!-- transl unclear here -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e893">
              To the second: the major premise is denied. With respect to the confirmation 
              <mentioned>it is said that in the divine essence there is an order of essential reasons</mentioned>, 
              it is said that such order intrinsically should not be admitted in any way, and
              does not put such an order in the Trinity.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e901">
              To the third: the antecedent is univerally conceded, but denied in the divine. 
              With respect to the confirmation: whatever is the case regarding the consequent, 
              the consequence is denied because living does not precede understanding, 
              nor does understanding precede willing, and nor does willing precede speaking because, as it was said, 
              there is no priority or posteriority.
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="pg-b1q5-Dd1e4375">
          <head xml:id="pg-b1q5-Hd1e4377"><supplied>Conclusions</supplied></head>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e912">
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q5-Qd1e4385">Hic oritur quaestio</quote>
              <bibl>Lombardus, I, d. 4</bibl>
            </cit>.
            This distinction I say contains four conclusions.
            First: it should be conceded that God generated God and one generated one, 
            nevertheless it should not be conceeded that God generated God himself or another God. 
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e923">
            Second conclusion: it is able to be conceded that 
            God the Father generated God which is not the Father.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q5-d1e929">
            Third conclusion: faith holds that the three 
            persons are one God, one substance, one essence, 
            and conversely that one essence is three persons. 
            And 
            <cit>
              <ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d4c2-d1e3487">the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name></ref>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d4c2-d1e3487">Lombard, Sent. I, d. 4, c. 2, [nn. 1-3], (I, 79-80).</ref></bibl>
              <!-- this target url only points to the paragraph containing the augustine quote. 
                I'm not yet sure the best way to refernece a sequence of resources, i.e. paragraphs 1-3, etc. -->
            </cit>
            proves this through 
            <cit>
              <ref>
                <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> I <title ref="#deTrinitate">De Trinitate</title>
              </ref>
              <bibl>Augustinus, De Trinitate, I, c. 6, n. 10</bibl>
            </cit> 
            to which according to the
            <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> 
            in this matter above all else faith should be consulted.
            Nevertheless it should be known that some authorities of scripture seem to be against the third conclusion, 
            where uncreated wisdom says about itself,
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q5-Qaaescs" ana="#sir24_14">I am from eternity and before the created age</quote>
              <bibl>Ecclesiasticus 24:13</bibl>
            </cit>.
            Item, 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q5-Qfcmpmf" ana="io17_5">Father clarify me the Son with the clarity which I had before the world came to be</quote>
              <bibl>John 17:5</bibl>
            </cit>,
            and all the other similar passages that are able to found. 
            From these passages it is clear that the terms said are signifying about the divine. 
            To the first of these it is said that this authority is understood thus: <mentioned>before the age</mentioned>, that 
            is, if there had been time before the age was in these things or while 
            these things were because, though God co-exists with each part of time, 
            nevertheless properly God is not in time, but in eternity or in an instant of eternity. 
            Thus in the same way the author authorities are able to be solved. 
            From what has been said it is clear that it does not follow: God is not prior because it was not, 
            therefore he begins or began to be.
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>