<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
 <?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Lecture 2</title>
        <author>Peter Gracilis</author>
        <editor>John T. Slotemaker</editor>
        <editor>Jeffrey C. Witt</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.1.0-dev">
          <title>Lecture 2</title>
          <date when="2015-12-24">December 24, 2015</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 License</ref></p>
        </availability>
        <date when="2013-10-10">October 10, 2013</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="L" n="lon">London, British Museum Royal 10 A I</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 
          guidelines for a critical edition.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2015-12-24" status="draft" n="0.1.0" corresp="versionlog.xml#v0.1.0">
          <note type="validating-schema">lbp-0.0.1</note>
      	</change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#L" n="15-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="pg-b1q2">
      <head xml:id="pg-b1q2-Hd1e3727">Lecture 2</head>
        <div xml:id="pg-b1q2-Dd1e3730">
          <head xml:id="pg-b1q2-Hd1e3732">
            Circa textum
          </head> 
          <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e3417">
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q2-Qd1e3742" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d1c1-vanspv">Veteris ac novae legis</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d1c1-vanspv">Lombard, Sent. I, d. 1, c. 1, (I, 55, ll. 5).</ref></bibl>
            </cit> 
            etc. Having completed the prologue a treatise follows in which the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> 
            does two things. For in the first place he provides a preamble, in the second place 
            he begins the matter to be treated. The second part begins in the beginning of the second distinction. <!-- reference to second distinction -->
            The first part is divided into three principal. For in the first part 
            the material of the books is distinguished and separated through distinctions.
            In the second part he introduces and treats some questions. 
            In the third part he takes up some of these things again and concerning what has been said 
            makes a conclusion. The second begins at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q2-Qd1e3757" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d1c3-d1e3612">cum autem homines</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d1c3-d1e3612">Lombard, Sent. I, d. 1, c. 3 (I, 58, ll. 13).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>. 
            The third at: 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q2-Qd1e3766" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d1c3-d1e3874">ergo ominum <unclear>qua<!-- dbcheck for quae --></unclear> dicta sunt</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d1c3-d1e3874">Lombard, Sent. I, d. 1, c. 3 (I, 61, ll. 3).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pg-b1q2-d1e175">
            The first part is further divided into two parts because in the first place the<name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> \
            inquires about the matter of these books in terms of division, secondly in terms of definition.
            The second begins at
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q2-Qd1e3779" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d1c2-faeand">frui</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d1c2-faeand">Lombard, Sent. I, d. 1, c. 2 (I, 56, ll. 10).</ref></bibl>
            </cit> 
            etc.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pg-b1q2-d1e196">
            The second principal part is divided into three inasmuch as the  
            <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> moves three questions: 
            first whether man is able to licitly enjoy himself; 
            second whether God enjoys man; third whether man licitly enjoys virtue.
            The second begins at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q2-Qd1e3791" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d1c3-d1e3728">sed cum Deus</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d1c3-d1e3728">Lombard, Sent. I, d. 1, c. 3 (I, 58, ll. 30).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>.
            The third at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q2-Qd1e3800">hic considerandum est</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d1c3-d1e3760">Lombard, Sent. I, d. 1, c. 3 (I, 59, ll. 20).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>.
            Some of these parts are divided <!-- should "divided" in latin be plural" --> into two because
            he introduces question, in the second place solves or offers the solution to the question. The parts are clear.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pg-b1q2-d1e243">
            The third principal <unclear>epilogitive</unclear> part is divided into two because in the first place he makes a conclusion, 
            in the second place he <unclear>indicates</unclear> the mode of things to be said and continues the things that should be said. 
            The second begins at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q2-Qd1e3840" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d1c3-d1e3874">de quibus omnibus</quote>
              <bibl>Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 1, c. 3</bibl>
            </cit> 
            etc.
            And this is the division in general.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="pg-b1q2-Dd1e3845">
          <head xml:id="pg-b1q2-Hd1e3847">
            Whether the supposite of created entity is an enjoyable object of the ordered will? 
              Or whether just as the created will is the subject of a related love, 
              so the blessed Trinity alone is the object of ordered enjoyment?
             
          </head>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e3518">
            Whether the supposite of created entity is an enjoyable object of the ordered will? 
            Or whether just as the created will is the subject of a related love, 
            so the blessed Trinity alone is the object of ordered enjoyment?
          </p>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q2-Dd1e3856">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q2-Hd1e3858">
              Principal arguments
            </head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e3531">
              The answer is no because the will is not the only subject of love, therefore.
              The antecedent is proved because love is cognition, 
              but the subject of a created cognition is in the intellect. 
              The major premise is clear because is not any more inconvenient 
              to say that love is cognition than to say assent is apprehension.
              Further because it would follow that someone would be blessed and would not see God.
              This is clear because if there are two acts, God would be able to preserve one 
              without the other.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e3547">
              In the second place the 
              Trinity is not the only object of ordered enjoyment, therefore. 
              The antecedent is proved since any creature  
              is infinitely loveable, therefore it is enjoyable in an ordered way.
              The consequence is clear because, if it is not enjoyable, 
              then it is loveable to a degree such that it can not be more loveable. <!-- i.e. "not infinitely loveable" --> 
              The first antecedent is proved through 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#HugolinoOfOrvieto">Hugolinum</name> in book one, conclusion three, article one</ref>
                <bibl>Hugolinus de Urbe Veteri, Sententia, I, d. 3, a. 1</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              Again, this is proved by 
              <cit> 
                <ref><name ref="#per-U89ddd">Fascinus</name> in his first book</ref>
                <bibl>Fascinus de Ast, Sententia, I, XXX</bibl>
              </cit> 
              because God loves any creature infinitely.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e3573">
              In the third place if the angel <name ref="#Satan">Satan</name> were to transform himself into the species of light, 
              a creature would be able to licitly enjoy him, therefore. 
              The antecedent is clear through the
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> in book one, distinction 30</ref>
                <bibl>Non invenimus</bibl>
              </cit> 
              and in  
              <cit>
                <ref>the same book, distinction two, question 1 <!-- this reference is unclear --></ref>
                <bibl>Non invenimus</bibl>
              </cit>, 
              where he says that, in such a case, the one believing the devil to be Christ is licitly able to adore him, 
              and this error would not be dangerous.</p>
              
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e3603">On the contrary is the  
              <cit>
                <ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d1c2-riqhud"><name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> in the present distinction</ref>
                <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d1c2-riqhud">Lombard, Sententia, I, d. 1, c. 2 (XXX)</ref></bibl>
              </cit>  
              quoting Augustine 
              <ref>
                <name ref="#Augustine">Augustinum</name>, in the first book  of <title ref="#deDoctrinaChristiana">On Christian Doctrine</title>, chapter 20</ref> 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q2-Qd1e3966" ana="Augustine_DeDoctrinaChristiana_1_5_5_a">res autem quae nos beatos faciunt 
                  et quibus fruendum est sunt Pater et Filius et Spiritus Sanctus</quote>
                <bibl>Augustinus, De doctrina Christiana, I, 5, 5 (XXX)</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q2-Dd1e3975">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q2-Hd1e3977">Prima conclusio</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e3628">
              The first conclusion about the supposite: though every 
              love depends on cognition causally, nevertheless any apprehension or cognition 
              of the object with the freedom of the will suffices to cause love
              The first is proved because, if not, it would follow that 
              love would be able to asserted or elicited naturally from the will, 
              without any cognition. The consequent is false 
              <pb ed="#L" n="15-v"/>
              because then the will would be able to love into infinity, 
              which opposes 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> in book XIII, 2, 10 <title ref="#deTrinitate">De Trinitate</title></ref>
                <bibl>Augustinus, De Trinitate, XIII, 2, 10 (XXX)</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              The consequence is clear because, having posited every cause required for the production of some effect, 
              with others having been excluded, such an effect would naturally be able to put into being.
              The second part is proved because <mentioned>if the cognition of the object alone</mentioned> etc., 
              it would follow that, given the judgement or apprehension of some object under the 
              aspect of evil with the existence of appearance of all things good removed, 
              the will would be able to wish or love such an object. The consequence is known, 
              but the consequent is contrary to the  
              <ref corresp="pg-b1q2-Qobaoba"><name ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name></ref>
              and the
              <ref corresp="pg-b1q2-Qobaoba"><name ref="#Averroes">Commentator</name> book I of the <name ref="#Ethics">Ethics</name></ref>
              because 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q2-Qobaoba" source="http://scta.info/resource/aa-ethica-1">all things desire the good</quote>
                <bibl>Aristotle, Ethica, I.1 (1094a1-3); Averroes, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e3692">
              The first corollary: that no love or volition 
              is essentially cognition or formally apprehension. This is clear because 
              the cause and effect are distinguished essentially. 
              And the antecedent is clear through the conclusion 
              because love depends causally on cognition and this on a type of 
              formal, material, or final cause, 
              therefore it depends on a type of efficient cause. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e3708">
              The second corollary: if love of the respect of some object 
              is in the will, then it is necessary with respect to the same thing 
              that the cognition be or be present in the intellect, when 
              speaking naturally or with respect to the common law. 
              This is clear through the conclusion because an effect presupposes its own cause.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e3727">
              The third corollary: if God is able to supply the exchange of some second cause, 
              he is able to cause love in the will.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q2-Dd1e4065">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q2-Hd1e4067">Second conclusion</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e3736">
              The second conclusion: it is both impossible that a created entity be intrinsically of infinite and unlimited goodness
              and it is impossible that any person has the intrinsic reason (ratio) of infinite loveability.
              The first is clear because uncreated nature alone is and is able to be intrinsically of unlimited goodness, therefore.
              The antecedent is clear through
              <ref corresp="#pg-b1q2-Qd1e4104">
                <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> <title ref="#onGenesis">Super Psalmos</title> 134 </ref> 
              saying that 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q2-Qd1e4104">solus deus est summe bonus cui nihil boni simpliciter de esse potest</quote>
                <bibl>Augustinus, Super Psalmos 134, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              This is confirmed because otherwise the creature would independent.
              The second part is proved because an created good thing is 
              insufficient unto itself and lacking another good, therefore 
              there is nothing that is infinitely loveable from its own intrinsic reason (ratio).
              The consequence is clear because something cannot be intrinsically more 
              loveable than its intrinsic goodness.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e3792">
              The first corollary: <unclear>no one</unclear> loving a thing <unclear>incomplexly and appropriately</unclear> ought 
              to extend the latitude of his love beyond the intrinsic worth of the thing loved.
              This is clear through  
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> IX <title ref="#deTrinitate">De Trinitate</title>, in chapter 9</ref>
                <bibl>Augustinus, De Trinitate IX, c. 9</bibl>
              </cit> 
              where he shows that to the degree that something is less good than God, in the same degree it ought to be less loved.
              And he concludes in the end that anything, which is not God, ought to be loved infinitely less than God.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e3820">
              The second corollary: no one loving God less than a creature enjoys or loves that entity appropriately.
              This is clear because there is an equal perversity in enjoying what should be used 
              and using what should be enjoyed.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e3828">
              The third corollary: it is both repugnant that someone should use God appropriately, and 
              repugnant that a creature justly enjoy a creature. This is clear because no creature has 
              as much goodness as God, therefore, nor as much loveability. Note that this is the proof of the preceeding 
              corollary. It follows corollarly that everyone positing that <mentioned>that God exists</mentioned> 
              is able to be demonstrated has to conclude: this being itself, which is above all things, ought to be loved. 
              This is clear from the force of the word, for God is 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q2-Qd1e4182">that which nothing greater can be thought</quote>
                <bibl>Anselmus, Proslogion, 3 (I, 103, II. 1-2)</bibl>
              </cit> 
              according to the rule of Anselm <name ref="#Anselm">Anselmi</name>. But to whatever 
              degree is the intrinsic goodness of something, so is the degree of its loveability 
              through what has been said, therefore.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q2-Dd1e4199">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q2-Hd1e4201">Third conclusion</head> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e3859">
              Third conclusion: just as the uncreated Trinity alone 
              is objective reason (ratio) of proper fruition, 
              so by the same token under a single reason (ratio) of the created image is there a motive 
              for enjoying itself. <!-- translation unclear here -->
              The first part is clear through 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> I <title ref="#deDoctrinaChristiana">De Doctrina Christiana</title></ref>
                <bibl>Augustinus, De Doctrina Christiana, I, XXX</bibl>
              </cit> 
              where it was stated previously. Again in 
              <ref>I <title ref="#Confessions">Confessions</title></ref> 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q2-Qd1e4229" source="http://scta.info/resource/Augustine_Confessions_1_1_1_a">ad te Domine nos fecisti et inquietum est cor nostrum donec requiescat in te.</quote>
                <bibl>Augustinus, <title>Confessiones</title> I, 1, 1 (CCSL 27, 1, ll. 6-7).</bibl>
              </cit> 
              This is confirmed because no creature suffices unto itself for existence or to live well, 
              therefore it does not suffice for another, and thus the ultimate and final rest 
              is not able to be found in a creature. 
              The second part is proved because, if 
              because if not, then would be the case that 
              <pb ed="#L" n="16-r"/> 
              it moves the intellect under the reason (ratio) of the true 
              and the will under the reason (ratio) of the good, but this
              does not work (impedit) because it is entirely the same reason (ratio) of goodness and immense truth. 
              But the immense Trinity does not demand that parts of the image should be enjoyed for their own sake, 
              except under the reason (ratio) of the truth and the immense goodness. Therefore, it is by one reason.
              <!-- paragraph hard to translate; needs second reader -->
            </p> 
            
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e3930">
              The first corollary: just as the uncreated Trinity under one 
              reason (ration) moves and shows itself beatifically in the image of a creature, 
              so it is not the case that the created image, the memory, 
              is elevated beatifically without the intellective (part) <!-- difficult translation -->
              The first is clear through the conclusion.
              The second is proved then because both because there is a single motion, 
              and because the thing moved and the thing received is the same, namely the memorative intellective power, 
              as seems to be the position of  
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> IX <title ref="#deTrinitate">De Trinitate</title> in chapter three</ref>
                <bibl>Augustinus, De Trinitate, IX, c. 3</bibl>
              </cit>.
              Nevertheless through this I do not wish to assert 
              that man would not be able to understand God clearly and not love him 
              because it is possible that he would see him clearly and not love him, 
              though he would not see him beatifically.</p> 
            
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e3975">
              The second corollary: it is both repugnant that the created image beatifically enjoy the divine persone with essence, 
              and that it enjoys the essence and not some intrinsic perfection. This is proved because 
              every divine perfection is formally and really the person and essence and vice versa.
            </p> 
            
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e3991">
              The third corollary: just as the Blessed Trinity more intensely and remissively vitally changes the enjoyable perception of itself, 
              so any object concurs causally and vitally for the perceptive perception of itself. 
              <!-- stefano notes this corollarium is almost Verbatim from Ripa Determinationes 
                also check John of Basel text here 
              --> 
              The first part is proved because it freely moves the created potency and freely effects the 
              total perception of itself, when it acts outside itself.
              From this fact it might be able to be inferred that, though the total and univocal cause 
              is not able to exceed the genus of the species, nevertheless a partial and equivocal cause
              is able to cause and effect beyond the perfection of its proper nature.
              The first part is clear in multiple places <unclear>in philosophy <!-- dbcheck --></unclear>. 
              The second is clear through what has been said since the material thing or object causally concurs for 
              cognition, which is immaterial. From what has been said the affirmative part of the question follows.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q2-Dd1e4277">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q2-Hd1e4279">Objections</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4017">
              Against the first conclusion and its corollaries it is argued since 
              any volition and love is formally cognition, therefore. 
              The antecedent is proved because, if cognition were destroyed in the mind, 
              while love remained with respect to the loved object, then it would be asked 
              whether or not through such love the object were known. If yes, the proposed position is obtained. 
              If not, then it would follow that one loves something unknown, which is 
              <cit>
                <ref>against <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name></ref>
                <bibl>Augustinus, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>.
              Again, with respect to this, the first principle argument made in opposition to question.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4045">
              In the second place, wherever there is a unity of the moving object under a single reason, 
              there is a unity of acts. But in the operation of the intellect and will, 
              at least in the enjoyment of heaven there is a unity of the moving object under a single reason,
              therefore there is a unity of acts, and as a consequence cognition and love, or loving and knowing, 
              will be the same non-plurified act. 
              The minor is clear through according to the second part of the third conclusion. 
              The major is clear through 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Aristotle">Aristotle</name> II <title ref="#deAnima">De anima</title></ref>
                <bibl>Aristotle, De anima, II, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4077">
              Against the second conclusion and its corollaries 
              it is argued in the first that 
              any creature is licitly able to be loved infinitely more than it is loved now, therefore. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4083">
              In the second place because God and every created multitude are infinitely loveable and 
              there exists <!-- "there exists" is an assertion that seems missing in the latin --> 
              something that is infinitely loveable and not God, but other than God. 
              Therefore something other than God is properly enjoyable.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4092">
              In the third place, God loves anything infinitely and immensely, 
              therefore anything is loveable infinitely.
              The antecedent is clear because God loves as much and in the same way as he is, since 
              his loving and his love and his mode of loving are really one and the same 
              with him who is the infinite and who is infinitely.
            </p>
            
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4103">
              In the fourth place against the second corollary, man is able to licitly enjoy 
              his neighbor more than God, therefore he licitly able to love him more. 
              The consequence is clear since to enjoy someone is to love someone. 
              The antecedent is clear because someone is licitly able to lament the death of a friend 
              more deeply (plus) and more enjoyable (fruentius) than the death of Christ, and more for 
              the damnation of temporal things than for the committed sins.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4122">
              Against the third conclusion it is first argued thus, the rational receptive potency of any creature 
              is finite and limited, therefore some limited goodness is able to beatify and finally satifisfy the creature. 
              The antecedent is proved because no creature is a greater perceptibility or capacity than an entity.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4139">
              Against the same conclusion it is argued, God alone finitely beatifies some blessed creature, 
              therefore finite goodness is able to supply its object influx in the perception of the creature. 
              The consequence is clear because to every given finite thing there is able to be given something equally 
              finite and better in perfection.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4150">
              Against the second part of the same conclusion, the object of the intellect and the will 
              is not able to move under the same reason, therefore.
              The antecedent is proved because the object of the intellect is intelligible as intelligible, 
              but the object of the will is a willable object as willable. But these things 
              differ by reason (ratio), which is proved in the first place by the fact that someone 
              is able today to be willing and understanding one object 
              and tomorrow to understand the same thing but not to wish it.
            </p>
            <!-- should this be its own paragraph ?? or should it be absorbed above -->
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4166">
              In the second place God understands today a man who he does not wish to love 
              and tomorrow he has understood and loved him. But this diversity is not in God, 
              therefore it lies in the obiectal <!-- objectal ?? --> reasons.
            </p> 
            <!-- should this be its own paragraph ?? or should it be absorbed above -->
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4175">
              In the third place God understands the evil of guilt and 
              yet he does not will it, therefore.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4181">
              Against the same part it is argued in the second place principally thus, it follows 
              that some part of the image is elicitive of enjoyment. The consequent is false because 
              enjoyment is an act of the will alone, since it is love or loving some thing on account of itself. 
              The consequence is clear because, if one does not elicit, then one is moved toward being elicited 
              and the other is not. Therefore it does not move by a single reason some part of them, which is 
              the opposite of this part.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q2-Dd1e958">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q2-Hd1e960">Responses</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4199">
              To the first objection the antecedent in the first place is able to be denied, and 
              for the proof it is said that, if love were to remain without knowledge, then 
              either God woudl supply the exchange of knowledge, as it was said in one of the corollaries, 
              or one would love mediately through a preceding ostensive cognition.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4212">
              In the second place it is able to be said that, 
              though love is able to be some experimental knowledge or perception,
              nevertheless it is not able to be our intellective cognition, or judicative, or indicative. 
              And through this is able to be solved the first argument in opposition to the question 
              by denying the antecedent. And for the first proof of this it is said that 
              it is not inconvenient to say that assent is apprehension because it pertains to the 
              intellect to assent and to apprehend. However to say that love is cognition, at least indiciative cognition, 
              is inconvenient.
            </p>
            <!-- this paragraph should possible be merged with the above -->
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4228">
              To the second proof it is said that no one is able to be perfectly blessed unless he sees God. 
              Therefore the consequence is denied just as
              <cit>
                <ref><name>Magister Honofrius</name></ref>
                <bibl>Honofrius, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>
              says.
              On this matter see 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Rimini">Gregory</name>, in book one, distinction 1, article 2, question 2.</ref>
                <bibl>Gregory Ariminensis, Sent., I, d. 1, a. 2, q. 2</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
        
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4242">
              To the second 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#AlphonsusVargas">Alphonsus</name>, in book I, distinction 1</ref>
                <bibl>Alphonsus Vargas, Sent., I, d. 1, q. 3, concl. 2</bibl>
              </cit> 
              would respond by denying the minor because he holds that, 
              in the enjoyment of heaven, the soul is not active but purely passive. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4252">
              In the second place it is able to be said that, though properly speaking 
              one potency moves causally effectively for eliciting an act, 
              nevertheless this motion is not formal and objective, 
              but only for the purpose of being perceived. 
              But here I speak about formal perceptive and objectal motion and not about the other kind.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4263">
              In the third place it would be able to be said that some beatifical potency in a single reason (ratio) 
              has or is able to find its proper object since its obiectal motion is freely presentative 
              which is not the case in other objects which naturally present and move themselves. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4271">
              To the third in the first place
              responds
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#HugolinoOfOrvieto">Hugolinus</name>, in distinction 1 of book 1, question 3</ref>
                <bibl>Hugolinus de Urbe Veteri, Sent., I, d. 1, q. 3</bibl>
              </cit>.
              I concede the antecedent in the following way, that from an infinity of will 
              it is possible to be loved more into infinity, but not from one will, see there. Additionally, 
              it can be responded by denying  
              <!-- end of first quire -->
              <pb ed="#L" n="17-r"/>
              <!-- new quire -->
              this consequence, 
              <mentioned>this creature is infinitely loveable, therefore it is enjoyable</mentioned>,
              unless this is added from the intrinsic worth of the thing.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4294">
              To the fourth the antecedent is conceded thus, by understanding that 
              <mentioned>nothing other than God</mentioned>, not including God or of which God is not a part,
              is <unclear>not <!-- should there be a "not" supplied here here--></unclear> infinitely loveable. 
              But in what has been proposed, this multitude includes God.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e1117">
              In the second place it is able to be said that this multitude 
              is loveable with more loves than God is, but not more intensely, or
              man out to which more good things to this multitude than to God, not nevertheless a greater good.
              Thus it would be possible to say that Christ should be loved more than the Father, that is, in more modes because 
              he died for us.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4314">
              To the fifth the antecedent is able to be denied.
              <!-- should this be a new paragraph -->
              In the second place this consequence is able to be denied, 
              <mentioned>some thing is loveable infinitely from an intrinsic reason (ratio), therefore it is enjoyable</mentioned>
              because it would then be required that by the reason (ratio) of some intrinsic goodness it would be intrinsically infinitely loveable. 
              Again it would be able to be said that, though it is loveable infinitely, 
              nevertheless it is not loveable infinitely.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4329">
              To another it is said that <mentioned>to enjoy something</mentioned> in said 
              in three different ways. In the first mode as cordial effection, in the second mode as bodily effect, 
              in the third mode as sensual exertion. But in the second and third modes of understanding the word 
              <mentioned>to enjoy</mentioned> the antecedent is conceded and the consequence is denied.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4340">
              To another against the third conclusion 
              <name ref="#ThomasStrasbourg">Thomas of Argentina</name> 
              would respond that the soul is of infinite capacity for an objectal non natural potency. See
              <cit>
                <ref>question three of the prologue, article one</ref>
                <bibl>Thomas de Argentina, Sent., I, prologus, q. 3</bibl>
              </cit>.
              Otherwise it would be possible to say that the soul is of an infinite capacity and of infinite perceptiveness, 
              though it is not an infinite perceptive potency nor infinitely, and the consequence would be able to be denied.
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#RichardKilvington">Kilvington</name>, in his third question</ref>
                <bibl>Richard Kilvington, Sent., I, q. 3</bibl>
              </cit> 
              says that the capacity of the soul is a finite substance, but it is an infinite capacity, 
              and thus he would deny the antecedent of the argument. Note the argument which he solves.</p>
            
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4367">
              To another I respond that God would be able to create one object so delightful that, 
              if God were to relinquish a soul of his nature, it would be as loveable in itself as in God
              and nevertheless it would not follow that such a soul would satisfy or beatify in the created object 
              because, though it is as loveable with this one, nevertheless it would be the case the creature 
              would still rather have that delight from God that from a created object.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4380">
              But against this response it is argued that either such a creature is able to freely 
              wish to have this delight from the creature just as from the creator or not. If the first, 
              then he is satisfied in the created good, against what has been said. If the second, then 
              it is not equally or in the same degree delighted in one as in the other, the opposite of which 
              is conceded by the case in question.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4390">
              Again a creature more greatly inclines to itself than to God, 
              therefore God is not the final end to which the creature is moved. 
              The antecedent is clear because, if the creature loves God, that is for his well being, 
              then whatever desires its own well being aims at its own conservation in being and being well.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4400">
              Again a rational creature is in objectal potency to being at rest in that in which God wills 
              for it to rest in. Therefore, a creature is able to find ultimate rest in created thing.
              The consequence holds because God is able to will this and to do so properly, and in the second place 
              because God is able to suspend his motion which moves the creature toward resting in God.
              Therefore it is said differently that no good below 
              the level of God is able to satisfy and beatify the soul and bring it to rest 
              because no good below the level of God is able to cause that kind of delight which 
              restful. Therefore according to the argument made by 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#HugolinoOfOrvieto">Hugolinsu</name>, in distinction one of the first book, in question three, near the end</ref>
                <bibl>Hugolinus de Urbe Veteri, Sent. I, d. 1, q. 3 (XXX)</bibl>
              </cit> 
              the consequence is able to be denied.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4429">
              Again it should be known that, though the creature is not able to come to final rest in the created good, 
              nevertheless it is able to believe that is at rest. This is clear because it would be able to have some
              created loveable thing such that he believes that is ultimate desirable things, even though 
              it is deceived on account of bad acts.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4437">Again it is the case that someone 
              does not know that God exists and takes as its ultimate end some temporal good,
              <pb ed="#L" n="17-v"/>
              and in this case the will is at rest in this and is deceived.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4446">
              In the last place it is able to be said that God is able to create something good 
              in which the soul is able to have as much <!-- translation of tantum difficult -->delight and rest, 
              where <mentioned>as much</mentioned> indicates the degree or latitude of an individual withing a species 
              and not of a species within a genus.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4457">
              To another against the second part 
              it is said that it is able to be distinguished because either such diversity of reason 
              comes form the co-rising (consurgentem) motion from the subject and predicate, and this is not against the conclusion 
              or comes from the object precisely, and in this case the antecedent is denied.
              And with respect to the proof <mentioned>because the object</mentioned> etc., it is conceded. And when 
              it is added <mentioned>but these things differ in reason</mentioned>, 
              it is conceded for creatures, indeed they even differ in reality, 
              but not in God. Therefore the argument against the conclusion does not succeed.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4478">
              To another proof, the consequence is denied, though perhaps it concludes that there is 
              not the same ratio of willing and understanding, but it does not support the distinction between the intelligible and willable. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4484">
              To another proof in the first place the consequence would able to be denied and the antecedent conceded. 
              In the second place consequent would be able to be conceded because he argues only for a difference in creatures.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4502">
              To another proof it is able to be said that just as the evil of guilt, since it is a deformity, 
              does not have the reason (ratio) of intelligibility, just as it also does not have the reason (ratio) of will-ability, 
              et thus the privation is not properly known through habit, so neither does sin, unless in the case that is some privation of the good. 
              <!--dbcheck above, translation difficult -->
              Note  
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#per-U89ddd">Fascinum</name> in the second</ref>
                <bibl>Fascinus de Ast, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>, 
              where he offers an example, saying that a man knows himself to be lacking a floren 
              not unless because in his mind he has the likeness of a flower upon which he is imagination is reflected, 
              and thus in his mind by such a species is caused the judgment of the missing floren. Thus he says further that 
              God knows there is not in Sorte, nor will there be, because thus he will have grace without 
              discontinuation.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4550">
              To another in the first place the consequent would be able to be conceded 
              by extending <mentioned>elicere</mentioned> to effect causally because then 
              enjoyment includes and act of the intellectu and thus enjoyment is not 
              only an act of the will, but also of the intellect. 
              In another mode the consequence is able to be denied when taking 
              <mentioned>enjoyment</mentioned> strictly just as he precisely speaks of the act of the will, 
              by holding the ration from the part of the moving object.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4564">
              To the last argument in the opposition it in the first place 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Bradwardine">Bradwardine</name></ref>
                <bibl>Bradwardinus, XXX</bibl>
              </cit> 
              and 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Holcot">Holcot</name></ref>
                <bibl>Holcot, XXX</bibl>
              </cit> 
              would say that such a person would enjoy the creature but would excused on 
              account of the unconquerable error and absolute ignorance.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e1448">
              In the second place <name ref="#HugolinoOfOrvieto">Master Hugolinus</name> would 
              say that such a person would not love the creature but God,
              and therefore would most especially be excused, in such an error were not occurring 
              from his guilt.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4588">
              In the third place  
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#JohnKlenkok">Master John Klenkot</name></ref>
                <bibl>Iohannes Klenkot, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>
              would say that such a person would be excused in part, 
              but not from the whole, because either such a person is in original sin or not. If the first, 
              then this error is the penalty for sin and is not excused. If not, but the person is in a venial sin, 
              still in the penalty of venial sin God is able justly allow some to fall into mortal sin, 
              and thus he is not excused because it is seem true that someone without any guilt should be permitted 
              by God to fall into error.
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="pg-b1q2-Dd1e4699">
          <head xml:id="pg-b1q2-Hd1e4701">Conclusions for the first distinction</head>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4607">
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q2-Qd1e4708" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d1c1-vanspv">Veteris ac novae legis</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d1c1-vanspv">Lombard, Sent. I, d. 1, c. 1, (I, 55, ll. 5).</ref></bibl>
            </cit> 
            etc. 
            This first distinction contains ten conclusions. The first is that what is treated in the sacred pages or 
            contained in the old and new law concerns specifically things and sign, and 
            by <mentioned>things</mentioned> he means those things which are no used from signifying something. 
            But a <mentioned>sign</mentioned> is said to be that which is used for signifying something. 
            Further some of these signs are not used except for the sake of signifying something, like legal sacraments; 
            others, not only signify but also speak (ferunt?) <!-- translation difficult --> because they help the 
            intellect, such as the evangelical sacraments or those belonging to the new law.
            
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4628">
            The second conclusion is that 
            <cit>
              <ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d1c3-d1e3874">in this first book of the <title>Sentences</title> the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name></ref>
              <bibl>
                <ref type="commentary" target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d1c3-d1e3874">Lombard, Sent. I, d. 1, c. 3 (I, 61, ll. 7-9).</ref>
              </bibl>
            </cit>
            will first determine about make determinations about things and then about signs.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4639">
            The third conclusion is that. 
            <cit>
              <ref>according to <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name></ref>
              <bibl>Augustine, XXX</bibl>
            </cit>,
            there are three types of things. For some are things that should be enjoyed, like the Father,
            <pb ed="#L" n="18-r"/>
            the Son, and the Holy Spirit, and the uncreated trinity, some are things that should be used, 
            namely the world and those thing which are in the workd; some are things that are enjoyed and used, 
            like ourselves and the holy angels. 
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4656">
            The fourth conclusion is that to enjoy is to inhere in something through love on account of the thing itself. 
            But to use something is to take something into the faculty of the will or to use something 
            is to use bring back (referre?) that which comes into use for choosing that which should be enjoyed. 
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4670">
            The fifth conclusion is that <mentioned>to enjoy something</mentioned> is called using something with joy, not merely in hope, 
            but in reality. And thus everyone who enjoys, uses, because they take something into the faculty of the will, 
            but the converse is not the case.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4678">
            The sixth conclusion is that the place where we enjoy perfectly, fully, and properly 
            is the place where we will see what we enjoy, namely in heaven. 
            In this life, however, we enjoy, but only imperfectly.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4685">
            The seventh conclusion is that no one ought to enjoy herself
            because no one ought to love herself on account of herself, but rather on account of that which should be enjoyed.
            Whence Paul, while enjoying Philemon in the Lord, was enjoying God rather than man. 
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4702">
            Eight conclusion is that God loves us by using us, not by enjoying us. 
            But this use, by which God uses us, aims toward our utility, not his, 
            and for his favor (voluntatem) alone.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4711">
            The ninth conclusion is that the virtues should be used well, not enjoyed. 
            But these virtues and other powers of the soul are thing powers through which we enjoy and use.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q2-d1e4717">
            The tenth conclusion is that the first it should be 
            treated about things which should be enjoyed, that is the only undivided Trinity. 
            And this is the opinion of this distinction.
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>