<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Lecture 3</title>
        <author>Peter Gracilis</author>
        <editor>Stefano Menegatti</editor>
        <editor>Jeffrey C. Witt</editor>
        <editor>John T. Slotemaker</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Lecture 3</title>
          <date when="2014-03-19">March 03, 2014</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 License</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="L" n="lon">London, British Museum Royal 10 A I</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 
          guidelines for a critical edition.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2014-03-19" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>File Started for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
        <div xml:id="starts-on">
          <pb ed="#L" n="18-r"/>
        </div>
      </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="pg-b1q3">
        <head xml:id="pg-b1q3-Hd1e3724">Lecture 3</head>
        <div xml:id="pg-b1q3-Dd1e3727">
          <head xml:id="pg-b1q3-Hd1e3729">Concerning the Text</head>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e88">
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qhivapf" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c1-d1e3473">Hoc itaque vera ac pia fide</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c1-d1e3473">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 2, c. 1 (I, 61, ll. 12).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>, 
            etc. 
            After <name ref="#Lombard">the Master</name> introduces some necessary preambles in the first distinction, 
            here consequently he continues to the things that should be said in this second distinction which is divided into two parts.
            For in the first part he puts the information of those studying the Sacred Scriptures, <!-- translation difficult here -->.
            in the second place he continues and proves in many ways his intention. 
            The second begins at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e3744" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c4-d1e3473">proponamus, ergo in medium</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c4-d1e3473">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 2, c. 4 (I, 63, ll. 19).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pg-b1q3-d1e152">
            The first part is divided into three parts because in the first place he teaches how those who are studying 
            ought to dispose themselves, in the second place he teaches which things and what sort of thins they ought to believe and suppose 
            in order to understand it, and in the third place how they ought to proceed in this study. 
            The second begins at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e3753" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c3-d1e3473">ceterum ut in primo</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c3-d1e3473">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 2, c. 3 (I, 63, ll. 9).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>,
            and the third at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e3763"><supplied>...<!-- need to supply what should go in the blank left in ms --></supplied>.</quote>
              <bibl>Non invenimus</bibl>
            </cit>.
            The first could be divided in three according to the three dispositions which he asserts. 
            For he teaches that someones studying ought to be pure and virtuous, careful and studious, calm and not quarrelsome.
            The second begins at
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e3775" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c1-d1e3511">de hac ergo re</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c1-d1e3511">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 2, c. 1 (I, 62, ll. 1).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>.
            The third begins at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e3784" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c1-d1e3524">proinde omnis qui audit</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c1-d1e3524">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 2, c. 1 (I, 62, ll. 5).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pg-b1q3-d1e224">
            The second principal part is divided into two. 
            In the first place he puts his conclusion or intention and proves it with the witnesses of the old law, 
            in the second place he declare it with the witnesses of the evangelical law.
            The second occurs at  
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e3793" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c4-d1e3723">nunc vero ad propositum</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c4-d1e3723">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 2, c. 4 (I, 65, ll. 24).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>.
            The first part is divided into two. In the first place he proves the simple unity of the essence, 
            in the second place he proves the threefold difference of the persons and the eternal equality of them. 
            The second occurs at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e3802" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c4-d1e3570">personarum aequalitatem</quote>
              <bibl cert="medium"><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c4-d1e3570">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 2, c. 4 (I, 64, ll. 9).</ref></bibl>
              <note xml:lang="en">Identification is somewhat uncertain, as Lombard has "personarum quoque pluralitatem" rather than "personarum aequalitatem".</note>
            </cit>.
            The second part now truly to the proposition at hand is divided into three parts 
            because in the first place he shows the unity of the essence and the trinity of the three persons at the same time, 
            in the second place he adds the duration of eternity, and in the third place he apologizes that he is not able to bring 
            more authorities to bear on this matter. 
            The second occurs at
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e3811" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c5-d1e3596">ipse et necessario sui evangelii</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c5-d1e3596">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 2, c. 5 (I, 68, ll. 3).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>. 
            The third occurs at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e3821" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c5-d1e3677">sed quia singulae poenae syllabae novi Testamenti</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c5-d1e3677">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 2, c. 5 (I, 68, ll. 15).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>. 
            And this is the division.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="pg-b1q3-Dd1e3830">
          <head xml:id="pg-b1q3-Hd1e3832">
            Question: Whether it is able to be proved through 
              the text of Holy Scripture that the creator of created nature 
              is three and one.
          </head>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q3-Dd1e3836">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q3-Hd1e3838">Principal arguments</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e119">
              Whether it is able to be proved through 
              the text of Holy Scripture that the creator of created nature 
              is three and one?
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e122">
              It is not able to be so proved because in the first place 
              God is not three and one, therefore etc. 
              The antecedent is proved because no incommunicable is communicable to three things. 
              But the Father is incommunicable and the divine essence is communicable. 
              Therefore the Father is not the essence 
              and consequently it is able to be argued about the Son and the Holy Spirit. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e125">
              In the second place because this is not able to be proved through a false text. 
              But the text of Scripture seems to be false or <!-- i think this "autem" should be changed to "aut" --> at least improper, therefore etc. 
              Minor is clear in
              <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e3879" corresp="#pgb1q3-Qldpdpc"><title ref="#hab">Habacuc</title> 2</ref>, 
              where it is said 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pgb1q3-Qldpdpc" source="http://scta.info/resource/hab2_11">the stones of the wall will cry out</quote>
                <bibl>Habacuc 2:11</bibl>
              </cit>.
              Again
              <name ref="#IsidoreOfSeville">Isidore</name> valet 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e3872">Why have you made us wander from your ways and you have made us to harden our harts, 
                  <pb ed="#L" n="18-v"/> 
                  so that we do not fear you?
                </quote>
                <bibl>Isiah 63:17</bibl>
              </cit> 
              Again
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e3887" source="http://scta.info/resource/lc7_22">the blind receive sight, and the lame walk</quote>
                <bibl>Lucas 7:22</bibl>
              </cit>,
              etc. 
              Again <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e3921" corresp="#pg-b1q3-Qd1e3902">the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> in book 5</ref>
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e3902">nothing is probable through scripture, which would have diminished faith</quote>
                <bibl>Not found</bibl>
                <note xml:lang="en">This text is not directly found in Lombard. 
                  It is possible that he means to cite the end (c. 5) of d. 2, 
                  which makes some sense. There the content is close, but the wording is different.
                  See <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e3936" target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c5-d1e3677">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 2, c. 5 (I, 68, ll. 15).</ref>
                </note>
              </cit>,
              but likewise to prove evidently the articles 
              would diminish faith and empty it of it is value, 
              therefore etc.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e163">
              On the contrary, the 
              <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> in this distinction seems to be opposed. 
              Again
              <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e3947" corresp="#pgb1q3-Qpshder">
              <name ref="#Augustine">Augustin</name> XIV <title ref="#deTrinitate">De Trinitate</title> in chapter one</ref> 
              says that
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pgb1q3-Qpshder" source="http://scta.info/resource/adt-l14-d1e1535">through 
                  the study of this science the saving faith is increased, defended, and strengthened</quote>
                <bibl>Augustine, De Trinitate, XIV, c. 1</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q3-Dd1e3934">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q3-Hd1e3936">First conclusion</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e188">
              First conclusion: though this proposition,
              <mentioned>if God himself is three and one</mentioned> is able to be sufficiently 
              deduced from a first principle, nevertheless that <mentioned>God is three and one</mentioned> 
              is not able to be concluded evidently from that first principle
              The first part is clear because, from the contrary of the consequent, 
              the opposite of the antecedent follows, therefore. 
              The consequence is valid, although we do not this to be evidently valid.
              The antecedent is since it follows, <!-- should we supply "if" here --> 
              God is not three and one, therefore God is not.
              For to the degree that is necessary that <mentioned>God is</mentioned>,
              it is to the same degree necessary that <mentioned>God is three and one</mentioned>. 
              The second part is proved because, 
              if it were possible to be concluded evidently from a first principle, 
              then this would either be a priori, and this not the case because this
              is not possible, or a posteriori which is not the case. 
              The latter is not the case because in the first place, 
              since some created effect is finite, 
              then such a proof would demonstrate that the first cause is finite. 
              Again in the second place, though every demonstration proceeds 
              from a created effect to a highest cause, this is insufficient 
              because it <!-- antecedent of "it" is ab bit unclear, the highes cause? but the similarities to what "God" or to the created effect? -->
              has more dissimilarities than similarities. 
              Further, given the fact that it might be possible 
              for someone to be persuaded through this argument
              that there is a first cause, 
              it would still in no way evidently convince 
              them that this highest cause is triune.
              On this point
              <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e3995" corresp="#pg-b1q3-Qnepsir">consider the words of the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> in this distinction</ref>
              saying: 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qnepsir" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d3c1-d1e3654">
                  Non enim per creaturarum contemplationem sufficiens notitia Trinitatis
                  potest haberi sine doctrinae vel superioris inspirationis revelatione</quote>
                <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d3c1-d1e3654">Lombard, Sent. I, d. 3 (XXX)</ref></bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e217">
              The first corollary is that many said or formable propositions about God 
              are deducible from the first principle. 
              This is clear from the conclusion, and this is confirmed in the case of the proposition
              <mentioned>God is not a stone</mentioned> because it is able to be deduced from the first principle 
              since the opposite proposition includes a contradiction. 
              For it follows, God is essentially a stone, therefore God is God, 
              therefore God is intelligent, therefore God is not a stone. 
              The first consequence is clear because the same this is predicate of itself. 
              The second is clear because given that is necessary that God is God 
              so it is necessary that God is intelligent. 
              And the third is clear because no intelligent this is essentially a stone.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e229">
              The second corollary: though every evidence argues for certitude, nevertheless not every certitude carries evidence. 
              The first is clear because everyone evidently knowing a conclusion is certain about that thing. 
              The second is clear because the fact that <mentioned>God is three</mentioned> is most certain 
              since is believed through faith, 
              and nevertheless we do not have evidence concerning this article of belief.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e241">
              The third corollary: just as it is repugnant that there is absolutely nothing, 
              so it is repugnant that three supposites are not really distinct. 
              From this it further follows that the following consequence is necessary: 
              there are not three things, therefore nothing is. 
              This is clear because it follows, if there are not three things, 
              then there are not three divine supposites, 
              therefore there is no God, therefore nothing is. 
              From this it is still inferred that it follows well, 
              there is one, therefore there are three because there are three divine supposites. 
              The consequence is clear because the opposite of the consequent 
              implies the opposite of the antecedent because it follows that, 
              there are not three things, 
              therefore there are not three divine supposites, there is not one.
              <!-- translation difficult here, need dbcheck from John -->
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q3-Dd1e4007">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q3-Hd1e4009">Second conclusion</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e251">
              The second conclusion: just as it is necessary in that within the divine 
              persons there is one super simple unity of essence, 
              so it is necessary that there is a real triune plurality or alterity. 
              This is clear from what has been said in the first conclusion. 
              <!-- is this correctly understood as reference to the first conclusion. If so a ref element should be added-->
              The is confirmed because it is in reality just as the conclusion signifies, 
              therefore that it is so is necessary. 
              The antecedent is clear from faith.
              The consequence is proved because in whatever sort of thing 
              is intrinsecally in the divine essence, it is necessary that such a thing is.
              This is clear  
              This is clear through
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4049" target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c2-d1e3473">the <name ref="#Lombard">Magistrum</name> in this distinction</ref>
                <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c2-d1e3473">Lombard, Sent. I, d. 2, c. 2 (I, 62, ll 15-24)</ref></bibl>
                <!-- need to leave note explain reference connection; also need to double check that target url points to the right place -->
              </cit>.
              Again through
              <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4064" corresp="#pg-b1q3-Qd1e4042">
                <name ref="#RichardOfStVictor">Richard</name> in his first book <title ref="#RichardOfStVictor_deTrinitate">On the Trinity</title> 
                chapter 27
              </ref>, 
              saying
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e4042">confidenter fateamur personas in divinitate secundum substantiam deitas et substantiam significare 
                  <pb ed="#L" n="19-r"/> 
                  et plures ibi personas, 
                  non plures substantias esse quia sunt plures habentes unum 
                  et indifferens esse ex differenti proprietate, unitas
                </quote>
                <bibl>
                  Richardus De Sancto Victore, 
                  <title>De Trinitate</title> IV, c. 19 (183, ll. 48-52).
                </bibl>
              </cit>.
              This are the words
              
              <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4091" corresp="#pg-b1q3-Qd1e4061">
                of the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> in this distinction, in the beginning
              </ref> 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e4061" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c1-d1e3473">hoc itaque</quote>
                <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c1-d1e3473">Lombard, Sent. I, d. 2, c. 1 (I, 61, ll. 1)</ref></bibl>
              </cit> 
              etc.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e287">
              The first corollary: not only in the divine is there solitude or singularity or simplicity of nature, 
              but also a true and real trinity of three equal persons. 
              This is clear from the conclusion, <!-- ref to above conlusion -->  
              whence in 
              <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4110">
                <title ref="#io">John</title>
              </ref> 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e4082" source="http://scta.info/resource/io14_16">alium paracletum dabit vobis.</quote>
                <bibl>Iohannes 14:16</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              Again in
              <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4128"><title ref="#Iio">I John</title></ref> 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e4098" source="http://scta.info/resource/Iio5_7">tres sunt, qui testimonium dant in caelo</quote>
                <bibl>I Iohannes 5:7</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              Again <name ref="#Athanasius">Athanasius</name> 
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e4109">alia est persona Patris</quote>, etc.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e323">
              The second corollary: though the paternal notional <unclear>utterance</unclear> 
              is to produce the son equal to itself, 
              nevertheless some speaking or understanding divine supposite is not producing the Holy Spirit. 
              The first part is from  
              <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4157" corresp="#pg-b1q3-Qd1e4129">
                <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> 
                in his book <title ref="#deTrinitate">De Trinitate</title>
              </ref> 
              saying
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e4129">
                  Pater dicens se genuit Verbum sibi aequale per omnia; 
                  non enim integre perfecteque se dixisset si aliquid minus se vel amplius 
                  esset in eius Verbo quam in se ipso
                </quote>
                <note>Augustine, de Trinitate, XV, 14, 23</note>
              </cit>. 
              The second part is proved because since a divine person understands itself and something other than itself, 
              it follows that the Son would produce either himself or another that is not himself. 
              Not the first since according to <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> 
              nothing is able to produce or generate itself, 
              and not the second because there would thus be a quaternity in the divine, 
              which is impossible and against the conclusion.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e350">
              The third corollary: just as is necessary that there be three supposites in the divine, 
              so it is impossible that the Holy Spirit produce something within it. 
              This is clear from what has been said because 
              it is true that it does not produce something internally, 
              therefore it is necessary, 
              therefore the opposite of this truth is impossible
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q3-Dd1e4147">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q3-Hd1e4149">
              Third conclusion
            </head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e361">
              The third conclusion: though the theologian through the text of 
              scripture is not able to show evidently that God is three, 
              nevertheless, through the same text, 
              he his able meritoriously to sufficiently approve and deduce the Trinity.
              The first is clear because the object of this article 
              is not evidently able to be deduced to the point of a contradiction, 
              as is clear from the 
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rcm381d" target="http://scta.info/resource/pgb1q3-d1e188">first conclusion</ref>
                <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pgb1q3-d1e188">Vide supra</ref></bibl>
              </cit>.
              The second part is proved because the article 
              is sufficiently expressed in Sacred Scripture, therefore etc. 
              The antecedent is clear in this distinction,  
              where the
              <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4196" corresp="#pg-b1q3-Qd1e4161">
                the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name>
              </ref> 
              ways
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e4161" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c5-d1e3677">singulae pene syllabae novi testamenti hanc ineffabilem <!-- confirm ineffabilem --> unitatis veritatem atque Trinitatis concorditer insinuant</quote>
                <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c5-d1e3677">Lombard, Sent. I, d. 2, c. 1 (I, 62, ll. 4-5)</ref></bibl>
              </cit>.
              But that the theologian meritoriously able to inquire and to teach and deduce through scripture 
              it is argued 
              <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4214" corresp="#pg-b1q3-Qd1e4188">
                from the words of <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name>
              </ref>
              and alleged by 
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4222" corresp="#pg-b1q3-Qd1e4188" target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c1-d1e3511">
                  the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> in this distinction
                </ref>
                <bibl>
                  <ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c1-d1e3511">Lombard, Sent. I, d. 2, c. 1 [n.3] <!-- don't have for numbers or para no. for newest edition --></ref>
                </bibl>
              </cit>
              saying that
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e4188">hac Trinitate nihil fructuosius invenitur</quote>
                <bibl>Augustine, De Trinitate, I, 3, 5 (PL 42:822)</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              Again
              <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4246" corresp="#pg-b1q3-Qd1e4203">
                the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> in his prologue
              </ref> 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e4203" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1prol-cadzdd">delectat nos veritas pollicentis</quote>
                <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1prol-cadzdd">Lombard, Sent. I, prol. [n.1], (I, 63, ll. 6-7)</ref></bibl>
              </cit>, 
              namely the hope of having eternal life which was one of 
              the moving causes for the compilation of his book. <!-- possible ref back to book one here? -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e404">
              The first corollary: No text of Sacred Scripture taken in its proper sense is false. 
              This is opposed to what 
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4270"><name ref="#Ockham">Ockham</name> says in his<title ref="#SentencesOckham">Scripto super Sententias</title></ref>
                <bibl>Ockham, Sententia, XX</bibl>
              </cit>.
              This is clear because otherwise the articles of faith would not be able 
              to be proven or deduced through this text, indeed Scripture would be rendered suspect.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e420">
              The second corollary: to study Sacred Scripture is a condition that increases merit. 
              This is clear, if it is understaken in love and on account of God 
              and is not repugnant to the catholic faith. 
              Indeed to study in any science that has not been prohibited is meritorious, 
              if it is commanded by a good act of the will,
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4287">as <name ref="#per-U89ddd">Facinus</name> shows</ref>
                <bibl>Facinus de Ast, XX</bibl>
              </cit>. <!-- Facinus of Asti -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e433">
              The third corollary is the affirmative part of the conclusion <!-- cross reference -->, 
              namely that it is able to be proven through the text of Sacred Scripture, etc. 
              This is clear through what has been said.
              
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q3-Dd1e4259">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q3-Hd1e4261">Objections and responses</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e443">
              Against the first conclusion it is argued: 
              through natural reasons we are able to know and to deduce 
              that the divine essence exists, therefore also that there is a Trinity of persons. 
              The consequence is known because whatever is known about the divine essence truly 
              coincides with the Trinity. 
              The antecedent is clear through 
              <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4319">
                <name ref="#Cicero">Tullius</name>, <title>De natura deorum</title>, 
                in the second book, after the beginning
              </ref>,
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e4286">omnibus enim innatum est et in anima quasi insculptum esse Deo</quote>
                <bibl>Cicero, De natura deorum, II, XX</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              To the same is Augustine
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4342">
                  <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name>, 
                  <title ref="Confessions">Confessions</title>, 
                  chapter 8
                </ref>
                <bibl>Augustinus, <title>Confessiones</title> 8, 2 (CCSL 27, 114-116)</bibl>
              </cit>, 
              speaking about the <name ref="#Platonists">Platonists</name>, 
              where he says that with reason itself he came to the knowledge not only of the divine essence. 
              but also of the Trinity.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e467">
              <!-- we need a link relation here to indicate that this is an object to conclusion 1 
                even though there is not explicit reference as there is in the paragraph above. 
                This relation could be asserted in the info.xml file but has to be something more than just 
                isRelatedTo. The idea that his an objection to the first conclusion not indicated in the paragraph itself 
                and is only know through the preceding paragraph. If there paragraphs were to be disconnected, 
                the nature of this relationship woudl be lost. The relationship could be something like "isObjectionTo" and 
                the inverse could be "isObjectedToBy" This is also true for arguments 2-4 -->
              The second is argued thus: every perfection found in creatures out to be attributed to God, 
              but to generate is a perfection in creatures, therefore.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e470">
              In the third place: to whatever degree nature is more actual, 
              so it is also  
              <pb ed="#L" n="19-v"/>
              more fertile. 
              But the divine nature is infinitely in act, therefore it is 
              of infinite fecundity.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e475">
              In the fourth place: every good thing is naturaly communicative of itself.
              But God is an infinite good, therefore.
              The major is from 
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4377">
                  <name ref="#Dionysius">Dionysius</name> 
                  <title ref="#deDivinisNominibus">On the divine names</title> 
                  chapter 12
                </ref>
                <bibl>Pseudo-Dionysius, De divinis nominibus, XX</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              And the minor is in 
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4394">
                  <name ref="#Anselm">Anselm</name> 
                  in his <title ref="#Proslogion">Proslogion</title> 
                  in many chapters
                </ref>
                <bibl>Anselmus, Proslogion, 2, 3, 13, 20 (I, 101-103, 110-111, 115-116)</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e499">
              Against the second conclusion: if there were three persons, etc., 
              it would follows that in the divine there is a relation and an opposition of relation, 
              therefore it <!-- this relation?? --> will be either only one thing or many.
              If only one, then there will only be two supposites or two persons. 
              But if many, then there will be at least four supposites which is a heresy.
              The consequence is clear because every relative opposition requires two extremes, 
              namely to generate to be generated, to spirate and to be spirated.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e502">
              <!-- same problem. We need to an assert a meaniful link relation even though the explicit reference 
                is only made in the precedeing paragraph -->
              In the second place it is argued thus: God is the same in every mode 
              in which it is better to be the same than not the same. 
              But to be the same essentially and personally is better than not to be the same in thse ways, 
              therefore. The major is clear through 
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4435">
                  <name ref="#Anselm">Anselm</name>, 
                  <title ref="#Monologion">Monologion</title> 
                  15
                </ref>
                <bibl>
                  <name>Anselmus</name>, 
                  <title>Monologion</title> 
                  15 (I, 28-29).
                </bibl>
              </cit>.
              The minor is clear because it is better that what suits the Father and any person exists than not exists.
              But to be the same essentially and personally suits each person,
              therefore being the same is better than not. 
              The minor is clear because any person is personally and essentially 
              the same as the divine essence.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e518">
              In the third place: it follows that there are three eternal divine persons, 
              and nevertheless not all three are eternal. 
              The consequent is implied. The consequence is clear 
              because through the conclusion and its corollary 
              there are three coeternal persons, and they are alos eternal. 
              But that there are not three eternal things is clear through 
              <name ref="#Athanasius">Athansius</name> who says 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e4427">there are not three eternal things but one</quote>
                <bibl>Athanasius, XX</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e526">
              In the fourth place against the second corollary: if through understanding, etc., 
              then it follows that any person will produce the Son. The consequence is clear because 
              everyone understands something, therefore it follows that this person produces himself 
              or something other than himself through understanding or loving. 
              This is confirmed because, if the Trinity of persons is compatible with simplicity, 
              by the same reasons it is compatible with quaternity because there does not 
              seem to be a reason why the Son is not able to produce the son through his own understanding 
              just as the Father.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e535">
              Against the third conclusion: that God is three is 
              nowhere expressly found in Sacred Scripture, therefore. 
              The antecedent is proved since, because Scripture has many senses and understandings, 
              it would be possible for and adversary to say that Christ and others who are speaking about the 
              Trinity were not speaking literally, but mystically and figuratively. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e545">
              Against the first corollary because there are many propositions which appear to false in the literal sense, 
              but this is the proper sense of Scripture, therefore. 
              The antecedent is clear in 
              <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4514" corresp="#pg-b1q3-Qd1e4486">
                <title ref="#io">John</title> 10
              </ref>
              ubi Christus dicit 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e4486" source="http://scta.info/resource/io10_9">I am the gate</quote>
                <bibl>Iohannes 10:9</bibl>
              </cit>.
              Again, 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e4495" source="http://scta.info/resource/io15_1">I am the true wine</quote>
                <bibl>Iohannes 15:1</bibl>
              </cit>.
              This is confirmed because the doctors of the scripture 
              contradict themselves, therefore. 
              The antecedent is clear from 
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4565"><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name></ref>
                <bibl>Augustine, XX</bibl>
              </cit> 
              and from 
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4575"><name ref="#Jerome">Jerome</name> <title>Super epistola Pauli ad Galatas</title> in many passages</ref>
                <bibl>Jerome, XX</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              Again, the antecedent is confirmed because the Gospel authors seem to disagree among themselves. 
              This is clear because, on account of this matter, Augustine seems to have written his
              book <title ref="#DeConsensuEvangelistarum">On the harmony of the Gospels</title>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e578">
              Again, against the conclusion and the second corollary: since the ones studying theology 
              expose themselves to the danger of erring, therefore no one ought to study theology, 
              nor is the study of theology meritorious. The antecedent is clear because within this study 
              are mixed in the words of the philosophers and heretics 
              which are neither licit nor helpful to read in their own right, as is clear from <name ref="#Jerome">Jerome</name>,
              who was seriously wounded by the fact that he read the books 
              <name ref="#Cicero">Cicero</name> as it his said in his legend. <!-- is this a reference to something? biography?hagiography?? a work by Jerome??-->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e587">
              Again, through the study of theology the habit of believing is easily acquired, 
              therefore through this study the one studying loses a circumstances that increases merit.
              The antecedent is clear. And the consequence is proved because the difficulty of believing 
              is a circumstances that increases merit, whence 
              <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4616">
                <name ref="#Jerome">Jerome</name> in some epistle
              </ref>
              says
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e4574">what is of greater merit is that which is of greater labor</quote>
                <bibl>Jerome, Exhortatio ad sponsam Christi, XX</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              Again 
              <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4631">
                <name ref="#Ambrose">Ambrose</name> in his book <title>On Cain and Abel</title>
              </ref>
              says,
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e4592">all virtue consists in labor</quote>
                <bibl>Ambrose, De Cain et Abel, XX</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e605">
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4654">the <name ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name> in book II of the <title ref="#Ethics">Ethics</title></ref>
                <bibl>Aristotle, Ethics, II, XXX</bibl>
              </cit> 
              seems to support the same point, 
              from which it seems to follow that it would be better to have 
              the status of a simple 
              <pb ed="#L" n="20-r"/>
              faithful pilgrim 
              than that of a profound or subtle doctor. 
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q3-Dd1e1332">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q3-Hd1e1334">Responses</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e623">
              To the first: whatever is the case concerning the antecedent, 
              the consequence is denied.
              For the proof it is said that the divine trinity is known by some and not known by some. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e629">
              With respect to the saying of <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> about the <name ref="#Platonists">Platonists</name>:
              in the first place it is said that <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> 
              does not say that he himself found this in the book of the <name ref="#Platonists">Platonists</name>,
              but in of some <name ref="#Platonists">Platonist</name>. 
              But there were many <name ref="#Platonists">Platonists</name> after the coming of Christ, 
              like <name ref="#Porphyry">Porphyry</name>, <name ref="#Plotinus">Plotinus</name>, et <name>Apuleius</name>, 
              who were perhaps good men.
              In the second place it is able to be said that if someone had known about the Trinity, 
              they would have had this from divine inspiration, just as 
              Secundo potest dici quod si aliquid noviter de Trinitate hanc habuerit ex divina inspiratione, sicut dicit 
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4706"><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> says in <unclear cert="low">hermete Mercurii</unclear> in the sermon <title>Contra quinque haereses</title></ref>
                <bibl>
                  <name>Augustine</name>, 
                  <title>Adv. Quinq. Haer.</title> 
                  III, 1-21 
                  (CCM 60, 264-268)
                </bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e670">
              With respect to the second: in the first place the major would be able to be denied 
              because to merit or to be able to merit is a perfection in creature, 
              nevertheless it is not able to be attributed to God. In the second place, 
              the minor would be able to be denied because perhaps to generate or to be able to generate 
              is an absolute perfection most especially in the divine because, according to what is commonly argued,
              since the Son is not able to lack any perfection.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e676">
              With respect to the third consequent would be able to be conceded because the 
              divine nature in the supposites of the Father and the Son is of an infinite fecundity 
              since the Father produces the Son in every way equal to himself, and the Father and the Son 
              produce the holy spirit consubstantial to themselves.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e680">
              The fourth: the entire argument is conceded and yet from this it is not evidently concluded that a Trinity of persons 
              is in the divine. Indeed it could be equally proved through this means a quaternity and quinternity, 
              perhaps even more than a trinity.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e693">
              To another argument: the minor would be able to be denied and for the proof it is said that, 
              though some person is of the same essence personally and essentially, 
              nevertheless it is not the case that same thing suits all three persons personally at the same time. 
              Again, it is able to be said that this major premise, in which it is said 
              it is better that what suits the Father or any person exists than not exist,
              is true if it is not relative but is only including a relation. 
              
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e699">
              To the third argument: it is said that the eternal or eternal things are able to exist substantively, 
              and thus are not three eternal things 
              but one eternal thing, or adjectively and thus there are able to be called 
              there eternal or eternal things. <!-- not sure how to translate the differnet gender and numbers of "aeterum/aeterni/aeternae" here -->
              In the second place, it would be able to be said that it is more properly said that the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit 
              are coeternal than eternal, therefore <name ref="#Athanasius">Athansius</name> concedes the first and denies the second.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e706">
              To the fourth: the consequence is denied and for the proof it is said 
              according to 
              <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4765"><name ref="#ThomasStrasbourg">Thomas of Argentina</name>, 
                in the second distinction of the first book, 
                in the first article, 
              </ref>
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e1492">
                that <mentioned>it is said</mentioned> is taken in two ways when applied to the divine. 
              
              In one mode properly, and in this case it is the same things as grasping the world. 
              And it is in this manner that  
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4782">
                  <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> 
                  VII <title ref="#deTrinitate">De Trinitate</title>
                </ref>
                <bibl>Augustine, De Trinitate, VII, xxx</bibl>
              </cit> 
                uses the word when he says that no one but the Father is speaking internally. <!-- is this is quote -->
                In another mode the word <mentioned>to say</mentioned> is take to mean to understand perfectly,
              </quote>
              </cit>
              and thus any person speaks itself,
              and in the same way it could be said about the word <mentioned>to understand</mentioned>. 
              It is in this way that
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4801">
                  <name ref="#Anselm">Anselm</name>, in the  
                  <title ref="#Monologion">Monologion</title>, 
                  <unclear cert="low">57</unclear> et 59 chapters
                </ref>
                <bibl>
                  Anselm, <title>Monologion</title> 57 and 59 (I, 68-70)
                </bibl>
              </cit>
              uses the term when he says
              individual persons speak themselves 
              any of them speak themselves. 
              But if an evident reason is sought for why the Son does not 
              produce the Son through his speaking just as in the case of the Father, 
              it is able to be said with 
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4826"><name ref="#Anselm">Anselm</name>, <title ref="#Monologion">Monologion</title>, 85o et 68o capitulis</ref>
                <bibl>Anselm, Monologion, non invenimus<!-- problematic; needs review --></bibl>
              </cit>, 
              that this transcends every act of human understanding.
              Through the same, the response to the confirmation is clear when it is said 
              <mentioned>by the same reason</mentioned> etc. 
              The consequence is denied, and when it is said <mentioned>because the argument does not seem</mentioned>, etc.,
              it is said that, though we know this properly but not perfectly, 
              nevertheless there is something to it,
              and therefore through believing we ought to take the intellect captive. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e756">
              To the first against the third conclusion: the antecedent is denied, for it is 
              clear in 
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4860"><title ref="#mt">Matthew</title> in the last chapter</ref>
                <bibl>Matthaeus, xxx</bibl>
              </cit>, 
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4872"><title ref="#io">John</title> in chapter 1</ref>
                <bibl>Iohannes, xxx</bibl>
              </cit>, 
              and also in the  
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4883">in <title ref="#liberextra">Decretals of the Roman Pontiffs</title></ref>
                <bibl>Decreti Romanorum Pontificum, xxx</bibl>
              </cit>, 
              in which, whoever would contradict, would be censured as a heretic. 
              Nevertheless I do not want to say that the <title ref="#liberextra">Decreta</title> are Sacred Scripture.
              quibus, qui contradiceret, censeretur haereticus. Nolo tamen dicere illa decreta esse Scriptura Sacra.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e768">
              To the second: in the first place the antecedent woudl be able to be denied, 
              when speaking about propositions which are put in the the text of Sacred scripture 
              not only narratively, but also assertively. 
              In the second place for clarity, note that the proper sense of any scripture 
              is the sense that the author Scripture intended by it. This is shown by 
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4898">
                  <name ref="#RichardFitzRalph">Armacanus</name>, in book one 
                  <title ref="#deQuaestionibusArmenorum">De quaestionibus Armenorum</title>,
                  in the beginning of this book.
                </ref>
                <bibl>Richard FitzRalph, De quaestionibus Armenorum, xxx</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-snqefp">
              <pb ed="#L" n="20-v"/> 
              In the second place, note that, since Scripture has many senses, 
              if the truth of some text is not able to be maintained according tone one sense, 
              one should run to another with which the other Scriptures better harmonize.
              And the highest care should be taken that the figurative expression 
              is not admitted to the literal expression, 
              and conversely that the true and proper expression is not changed 
              into a figure and through to be figurative.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e781">
              In the third place, it should be noted that, 
              though through scripture something can be signified through a likeness, 
              nevertheless it is not necessary on account of this 
              that the same thing in one place signifies one thing 
              through this same word through a likeness. <!--db check, translation difficult here -->
              This notable is asserted by 
               
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4918"><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> III <title ref="#deDoctrinaChristiana">De doctrina Christiana</title></ref>
                <bibl>Augustine, De doctrina Christiana, III, xxx</bibl>
              </cit>
              and he offers an example about everything.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e791">
              To the confirmation, 
              it is said that doctors are not authors of Sacred Scripture, but only expositors.
              Concerning the evangelists it is said that in no passage are they really discordant. And accordingly <!-- accordingly for "insignum" --> 
              his book is not called
              <mentioned>on the discord</mentioned> but <mentioned>on the concord of the evangelists</mentioned>.
              Nevertheless if it were called 
              <mentioned>on the discord</mentioned>, 
              this would not be true and real, but only an assessment or an opinion and mere words.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e806">
              To another: 
              the antecedent is denied, if one studies in the way they ought. 
              For such a person ought not to seek to understand in order to believe, 
              but  
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qd1e4896">believe in order to understand</quote>
                <bibl>Anselm, Prosologion, 1, (I, 100, ll. 18-19)</bibl>
              </cit> 
              as
              <ref xml:id="pg-b1q3-Rd1e4953">
                <name ref="#Anselm">Anselm</name> 
                says
                at the end of the prologue of his <title ref="#Proslogion">Proslogion</title>
              </ref>.
              To the proof <mentioned>concerning the sayings of the heretics</mentioned>, etc., 
              it is said that reading such words is licit when it is for the learning of what is true and 
              the rebuke of what is false. But such reading is not licit when it is 
              for the purpose of believe or imitation 
              or the vanity of assertion or the inordinate delight.
              And perhaps therefore <name ref="#Jerome">Jerome</name> was flogged and beaten because 
              he was reading with delight since perhaps on account of that love 
              he was missing the better and more useful parts.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e822">
              To the last: it is said that, though the one studying believes more easily, 
              nevertheless his merit does not diminish on account of this because in this case 
              he acquires better things, such as to believe more intensely or extensively, more expressly or more truly. 
              For through a habit of this type he subordinates faith to his love and actually directs it into God. .
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e828">
              In the second place it would be able to be responded by denying the antecedent 
              because the more subtile theologian does not always believe more easily, indeed 
              many arguments and objections arise for the theologian that do not bother the simple believer.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e831">
              From what has been said it is clear that it does not follow from these things <!-- things?? eis? -->
              that through the study of theology there is acquired,  with respect to the articles, a knowledge superior to faith.
              Therefore the same thing is evident and inevident, evident through science, inevident through faith. But 
              it follows that one assents to an article through some means 
              that does not come from scientific evidence.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e840">
              The first argument to the contrary: in the first place it would be possible to say that 
              when taking <mentioned>communicable</mentioned> as communicated to another,
              it is distinct from the one to whom it is communicated. In this way it is 
              said that the essence is not properly communicable.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e843">
              In the second place, it is said, by following the common school and the mode of speaking 
              of the doctors, that the essence is communicable and not the person. And then the 
              major premise is able to be understood in two ways.
              In one mode nothing incommunicable is communicable to three things, 
              that is, it is not something which is communicated to three things, 
              and thus the major premise is false.
              In another mode nothing incommunicable <!-- is something missing here -->, that is, 
              this is not able to be communicated to three things, 
              and then the major premise is true, but form of arguing is not valid.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q3-aadqsr">
              To the other two it is clear through what has been said what should be responded.
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="pg-b1q3-Dd1e4948">
          <head xml:id="pg-b1q3-Hd1e4950">
            Conclusiones pro secunda distinctione
          </head>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e85">
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q3-Qhivhiv" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c1-d1e3473">Hic itaque vera</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d2c1-d1e3473">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 2, c. 1 (I, 61, ll. 12).</ref></bibl>
            </cit> 
            this second distinction contains three final sentential conclusions.
            The first: that the Trinity of divine persons is the only one and true God.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q3-scqeap">
            The second conclusion: that in God is a 
            unity of essence or substance and a trinity of persons. 
            Therefore there are not three gods but one God, 
            though the Father generated the Son, 
            and therefore the Son is not the who is the Father, and the Son is generated from the father, 
            therefore the Father is not who the Son is, and the Holy Spirit is not the Father nor the Son, but the spirit
            <pb ed="#L" n="21-r"/> 
            is only coequal and consubstantial to both Father and the Son. Nor in this case are 
            they different <!-- aliud et aliud --> neutrally, rather they are different <!-- alius et alius --> personally.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q3-d1e90">
            Third conclusion: that ever catholic writer who has written about the Trinity 
            which is God intends to teach that the Father and Son and Holy Spirit 
            are of one substance and essence and are one God with an inseparable equality. 
            And this unity in essence and trinity in persons is proved through many scriptures 
            and in many testimonies of holy doctors. Moreover the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> ads 
            near the beginning of this distinction that this highest good, 
            namely God the Trinity, is only recognized by minds purged through faith.
            And this concludes this distinction.
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>  
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>