<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Book I, Question 6</title>
        <author>Peter Gracilis</author>
        <editor>Jeffrey C. Witt</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Book I, Quaestio 6</title>
          <date when="2015-07-03">July  04, 2014</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 License</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="L" n="lon">London, British Museum Royal 10 A I</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-critical-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 
          guidelines for a critical edition.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2015-07-03" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>File Started for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="include-list">
        
      </div>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#L" n="25-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="pg-b1q6">
        <!-- TODO: dbcheck all instances of "generated" consider whether they should be "beget" or whether or not generate is an ok translation for gignere" -->
        <head xml:id="pg-b1q6-Hd1e3498">Quaestio 6</head>
        <div xml:id="pg-b1q6-Dd1e3501">
          <head xml:id="pg-b1q6-Hd1e3503">
            <supplied>About the text</supplied>
          </head>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e83">
            <pb ed="#L" n="26-r"/>
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q6-Qd1e3515" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d5c1-d1e3476">Post haec queritur</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d5c1-d1e3476">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 5, c. 1 (I, 80, ll. 26-27).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>.
            This is the fifth distinction in which, after the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> showed how 
            it should be conceded that <mentioned>God generated God</mentioned>, 
            now the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> introduces the question 
            concerning begetting and the begetted. 
            And this is divided into three because in the first place he 
            introduces the new <!-- new for "variam" --> question, in the second place 
            it offers the solution to the question, 
            in the third place he expounds on many authorities 
            and explains the different intention of each of them. 
            The second begins at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q6-Qd1e3538" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d5c1-d1e3479">ad quod catholicis</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d5c1-d1e3479">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 5, c. 1 (I, 81, ll. 2).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>.
            The third at
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q6-Qd1e3547" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d5c1-d1e3830">dicitur quoque</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d5c1-d1e3830">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 5, c. 1 (I, 85, ll. 2).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e110">
            The second part is divided into two 
            because in the first place he shows that divine power is not generated passively, 
            in the second place that it does not generate actively. 
            The second begins at
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q6-Qd1e3559" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d5c1-d1e3592">itaque non est dicendum</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d5c1-d1e3592">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 5, c. 1 (I, 82, ll. 16).</ref></bibl>
              <note xml:lang="en">While this could also be a reference to 
                <ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d5c1-d1e3482">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 5, c. 1 (XXX).</ref>. 
                The above identification, based on the sense of the discussion is a better match.</note>
            </cit>.
            The first could be divided into many parts according to which the
            <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> offers his intention.
            In the second, he objects against it. 
            The parts will be clear while reading, 
            and this is the distinction, etc.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="pg-b1q6-Dd1e3580">
          <head xml:id="pg-b1q6-Hd1e3582">
            <supplied>Question: Whether it is repugnant that many causes effect something 
            totally and it is repugnant that the same things really produces itself.</supplied>
          </head>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e125">Whether it is repugnant that many causes effect something 
            totally and it is repugnant that the same things really produces itself?</p>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q6-Dd1e3586">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q6-Hd1e3588">Principal arguments</head>
            <p xml:id="pg-b1q6-d1e3594">That not because 
              de facto many causes totally effect some thing, which is clear in the first place 
              because God and the created will are total causes 
              of the free acts of the created will.
              Therefore it follows that God is a total cause of these acts. 
              This is clear because the whole act and any part of it 
              depended totally on God to come into being and to be conserved. 
              But it also follows that the will is a total cause of these acts. 
              This is clear because other there would not be some portion of the act of the will 
              that be effectively from the will, and thus it would be in within its power, 
              which is  
              <cit>
                <ref>against <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name></ref>
                <bibl>Augustine, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e170">
              Secondly, if two fires equally disposed are applied to something combustible like wood,
              in every circumstance, one of them would be the total cause of the combustion, 
              which is clear because any one of them is a sufficient cause of combustion, 
              which when posited, the effect follows.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e181">
              Thirdly, 
              the divine essence is the generative principle of itself and the subject of its own generation, therefore.
              The antecedent is clear because there does not seem to be another principle by which 
              or in which something could be internally generated except in the divine essence.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e189">
              On the contrary it is argued, because one of these is impossible and there is no range of impossibility 
              because all impossible things are equally impossible.
              </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q6-Dd1e3632">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q6-Hd1e3634">
              <supplied>First conclusion</supplied>
            </head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e197">
              First conclusion: though some effect on account of itself and something of its own 
              depends effectively causally on many things, 
              nevertheless it is not the case that the same effect depends equally on 
              several total causes.
              The first part is clear through first argument made before the opposite 
              about the acts of the will.
              The second part is proved because the first cause influences the effect more and more perfectly 
              than the second, therefore. 
              The consequence holds because the first cause 
              necessarily requires the production of some effect, as I suppose. 
              The antecedent is clear 
              <cit>
                <ref>through the author of the <title ref="#deCausis">Book of Causes</title></ref>
                <bibl>Librum de Causis, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              This is also clear because the first cause independently causes and influences, 
              therefore it does not do so equally with the second.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e252">
              The first corollary: though with respect to the same thing there are many total causes 
              in the totality of the caused effect,
              nevertheless it is not the cause that with respect to the same thing 
              there are at one and the same time many total causes 
              in the precise causal totality. This is clear through the conclusion  <!-- totum is unclear not sure how to translate --> 
              and entire corollary.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e269">
              The second corollary: that it does not follow that, 
              <c>a</c> is in some mode the total effective cause 
              of <c>b</c>, therefore, when <c>a</c> has been posited with by some remote divine influence 
              <c>b</c> does not follow.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e293">
              The third corollary: that this consequence also does not follow, 
              <c>a</c> totally produces <c>b</c>,
              therefore nothing other than <c>a</c> produces <c>b</c>. 
              The same this is clear because 
              the opposite of the consequent stands 
              with the antecedent taken in the stated mode.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e324">
              From what has been said it could be further inferred that 
              for the production of a fly as many productive things or active potencies 
              are required as are required for the generation of the word in the divine essence.
              This is clear because in both cases an immense potency is required. 
              This is clear through what has been said.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q6-Dd1e3719">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q6-Hd1e3721">
              <supplied>Second conclusion</supplied>
            </head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e332">
              The second conclusion: though in the divine essence the name of cause is not intrinsically posited, 
              nevertheless the ratio of a beginning in the divine is not denied.
              The first is clear because 
              the cause is called the being to being of which another follows. But in the divine essence 
              one thing does not follow to another because there nothing is prior or posterior, 
              nor is there a giving substantively of one thing and then another, therefore. 
              The antecedent is clear
              <cit>
                <ref>in book V of the <title ref="#Metaphysics">Metaphysics</title></ref>
                <bibl>Aristoteles, Metaphyisca, V, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>.
              The second part is proved because truely the Son in the divine is from the Father 
              and the Holy Spirit is from both of them, 
              therefore the ratio of a beginning should be put in the divine.
              The consequence holds because according to 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name>, book V <title ref="#Metaphysics">Metaphysics</title></ref>
                <bibl>Aristoteles, Metaphyscia, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>,
              the beginning 
              <pb ed="#L" n="26-v"/> 
              is that from which something has its being. 
              The antecedent is clear because in the Symbol
              <title>Symbol of <name ref="#Athanasius">Athanasius</name></title> 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q6-Qd1e3786">the Son is from the Father alone</quote>
                <bibl>Symbolum Athanasii, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>, 
              etc.
              Again
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q6-Qd1e3795">The Holy Spirit is from the Father and the Son</quote>
                <bibl>Symbolum Athanasii, XXX</bibl>
              </cit> 
              etc. 
              This is confirmed because, 
              according to <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name>,
              the Father is the beginning without a beginning, 
              and the Son is the beginning from the beginning.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e384">
              The first corollary: 
              only the uncreated Trinity is able to be called properly
              the total and sufficient cause of any creature.
              This is clear because, having posited its causality with respect to anything externally producible thing, 
              while everything else set aside, something else follows, that is the effect, and this is to be the proper 
              cause according to what the proof of the conclusion says.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e394">
              The second corollary: though in created things the beginning and the cause are convertible, 
              nevertheless in the divine they are not said in the same way.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e400">
              Third: that no creature or producible entity necessary 
              demands several efficent causa for being. 
              This is clear because the first cause alone suffices.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q6-Dd1e3816">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q6-Hd1e3818">
              <supplied>Third conclusion</supplied>
            </head> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e413">
              The third conclusion: though something that 
              implies a contradiction is not able to be caused by the first cause, 
              nevertheless whatever formally and properly includes a contradiction 
              is able to become and produced. 
              The first part is proved because the first cause or God 
              is something that does not include a contradiction. 
              But God is not able to be caused by something, therefore.
              The major premise is proved because 
              no simple or incomplex entity includes a contradiction. 
              The second part of the antecedent is clear 
              because if God were able to be caused, 
              it would either be by himself or by something else. 
              He is not cause by something because 
              every other cause depends on God to be conserved and to act, 
              as has been said. 
              Not the second because according to  
              <ref>
                <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name>, book I of <title ref="#deTrinitate">De Trinitate</title>, 
                chapter one
              </ref> 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q6-Qd1e3838">no thing is that which begets itself</quote>
                <bibl>Augustine, De Trinitate, I, 1, 1 (XXX)</bibl>
              </cit>.
              The second part of the conclusion is proved 
              because only propositions formally and properly include contradiction.
              However all such things are formable by the first cause, therefore 
              
              Secunda pars conclusionis probatur quia solae propositiones formaliter et proprie contradictionem includunt,
              sed omnes tales sunt a prima causa formabiles, 
              <app>
                <lem>ergo</lem>
                <rdg wit="#L" type="correction-addition">
                  <add>ergo</add>
                </rdg>
              </app>
              <supplied>etc.</supplied>.
            </p>
            
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e467">
              The first corollary: that the formal ratio of the term 
              and also of the principle by which the Son 
              was formally generated or the Holy Spirit was spirated 
              does not belong to the divine essence, 
              but is rather denied by it. 
              This is clear because otherwise the same thing 
              would beget itself which is contrary to what has been said 
              in the question and against  
              <cit>
                <ref>the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> in this distinction</ref>
                <bibl><ref>Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 5, c. 1 (I, 81-82).</ref></bibl>
              </cit>. 
              Again, 
              in favor of this corollary is the determination of the Church
              Item, 
              pro isto corollario est determinatio ecclesiae 
              <ref><title>Extra</title>, de summa Trinitate et fide catholica, capitulo dampnamus</ref> 
              where it is said that
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q6-Qd1e3889">the divine essence neither generates or is generated</quote>
                <bibl>Liber Extra, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              Again, this is proved by  
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Rimini">Gregory our Doctor</name> in this distinction, article 4</ref>
                <bibl>Rimini, Sent., I, d. 5, a. 4 (XXX)</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e492">
              The second corollary: just as the divine essence 
              is not the formable productive principle of divine generation, 
              so it is not the material subjective principle of the same.
              The first part is clear through what has been said. 
              The second part is clear because the divine essence is not able to be perfected, 
              therefore it is not able to be subjected to this generation. 
              The consequence is clear because the terminus of any generation 
              perfects its subject. The antecedent is clear in itself. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e504">
              The third corollary: 
              Tertium corollarium 
              <mentioned>God is not</mentioned>, 
              <mentioned>a Chimera exists</mentioned>, 
              <mentioned>the whole is less than its parts</mentioned>, 
              <mentioned>contradictories are true at the same time</mentioned> 
              do not formally and properly include contradictions. 
              This is clear through 
              <cit>
                <ref>
                  the second part of the conclusion, 
                  <mentioned>since they include</mentioned>
                </ref>
              </cit> 
              because  
              such things are not able to become 
              from a first cause. 
              The affirmative part of the conclusion is clear 
              from what has been said.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q6-Dd1e3942">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q6-Hd1e3944">
              <supplied>Objections</supplied>
            </head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e517">
              Against the first conclusion
              there seem to be two reasons made in the opposition to the question.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e521">
              In the second place against the second part,
              it is argued, since many things are able to be the 
              causes of some effect, given that one of them is posited, 
              it follows that the effect is also posited. 
              But to be a cause in this way is to be the total cause, therefore.
              The antecedent is clear from the two fires, form 
              the many ships which are pulling of <!-- transl difficult here -->
              which the middle would be able to pull the ship in this case, 
              and from many other examples.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e531">
              In the third place, if the first part of the conclusion and the first corollary were true, 
              it follows that the
              <cit>
                <ref>saying of the <name ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name></ref>
                <bibl>Aristoteles, XXX</bibl>
              </cit> 
              is false, in which it is said that an efficient cause is sufficient, 
              such that when posited, the effect is also posited, 
              and, when removed, it is removed.
              The consequence is clear because, 
              when the causality of the will within respect to some act of the will 
              is posted, the effect does not follow, 
              unless there is also posited some concurrent cause, think God, therefore.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e550">
              Against the second part of the second conclusion, 
              if the ratio of the beginning were instead to suit a divine person, 
              it follows that it would be possible that some divine supposite is begun. 
              The consequent is not conceded, 
              and the consequence is clear because 
              the beginning and the begun are correlatives, 
              which are said to correlate at the same time.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e558">
              In the second place against the first corollary, 
              if God were the sufficient and total cause of any create effect, 
              it would follow that a second 
              <pb ed="#L" n="27-r"/>
              cause produces something in vain.
              The consequent is false. 
              The consequence is clear because, 
              if the second cause did not act, 
              the effect would nonetheless still follow, therefore.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e567">
              In the third place against the third corollary, 
              if some entity for its own generation does not need several efficient causes, 
              it follows that God alone would be able to produce in something hatred of himself.
              The consequent is false, since this act is necessarily involved in wickedness, 
              and the consequence is clear because every act is a producible entity.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e606">
              Against the first corollary of the third conclusion, 
              it is argued that the essence generates and is generated. 
              In the first place thus, every divine essence or Son is generated, 
              the whole Trinity is the essence or the Son, therefore 
              the whole Trinity is generated. 
              The premisses are true and the form is good, as it is seen, therefore.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e614">
              In the second place thus, 
              something generates in the divine, 
              and this is nothing other than the essence, 
              therefore.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-thpoeg">
              In the third place, 
              this Father generates,
              this Father is the essence, 
              therefore this essence generates.
              And this is able to be reduced to 
              the first mode of the first figure,
              <!-- could be a seg type for syllogisms; if so it could be added here. -->
              every father generates, 
              every essence is the Father,
              therefore every essence generates.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e626">
              In the fourth place, what is generating is the divine essence, 
              therefore the divine essence is generating. 
              The consequence is clear through the conversion absolutely speaking. 
              The antecedent is proved 
              because the Father generating is the essence, 
              therefore what is generating is the essence.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e634">
              In the fifth place, 
              the Father is both convertible to the essence 
              and the essence would be convertible tot he Father, 
              if its only suppositum were the Father, 
              but then, whatever would be said about the Father, 
              would be said about the essence, 
              therefore. Now it is thus, therefore, 
              just as generating is said of the Father, 
              so it is also able to be said of the essence.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e644">
              In the sixth place, 
              the divine essence is not not-generating and it exists, 
              therefore it is generating.
              The consequence seems to be known. 
              The antecedent is proved 
              because whatever is in the divine is 
              either generating, or generated, or proceeding.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e652">
              Against the second corollary of the same conclusion, 
              it is proved that the divine essence is the subject of divine generation 
              because that which remains under each term has the ratio of a subject. 
              The divine essence is of this type, therefore.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e659">
              Secondly, to any active potency there corresponds a passive potency. 
              But in the Father there is an active potency, 
              therefore in the Son there is something passive. 
              But this is not the relation, therefore it is the essence.
              
              Secundo, cuilibet activae potentiae correspondet passiva potentia sed in patre est activa potentia ergo in filio 
              est aliquid se habens passive sed hoc non est relatio ergo essentia.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e666">
              Thirdly, 
              because the following propositions is conceded 
              <mentioned>the Son is from the Father</mentioned>,
              it is therefore conceded that the word <mentioned>a</mentioned>
              connotes that the circumstance of either the causal origin or material principle.
              If the first, then
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> conclueds nothing in <title>Contra Maximum</title>, in book 3</ref>
                <bibl>Augustine, Contra Maximum, III, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>
              because <name>Maximus</name> conceded that the 
              Son is from the Father. 
              If the second, the proposed is obtained 
              because in the generation of the Son the essence is the subject.
              For the solution of the argument 
              it should be known that 
              the fact that something is a cause or depends totally on a cause 
              is able to be taken in two ways.
              In the first mode because the entire effect and 
              whatever is effective of it effects it without another cause.
              In the second mode, that the entire effect and anything of it 
              effects in isolation with any other efficient cause. 
              According to the first mode given about the total effective cause or the effective dependence, 
              I have posited and I understand the first part of the first conclusion and therefore the first part o
              of its first corollary, and there the two other corollaries. 
              But according to the second sense given about the total cause, I have put the second part of the conlusion 
              and the second of its corollaries, as is clear to the one looking.
            </p> 
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q6-Dd1e884">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q6-Hd1e886">Responses</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e729">
              To the first, therefore the antecedent, consequent, and consequence 
              are conceded concerning the total cause in the first sense, but not in the second, because, 
              if the antecedent were taken in the second sense, then it would be false 
              because in this sense God alone is the total cause because no second cause 
              is able to cause an effect with him. 
              Nevertheless having supposed the general divine influence, 
              it is still able to be said there are able to be several total causes 
              with respect to effect, especially if the same effect is able to be produced 
              by diverse created causes and by one without the other. 
              And in this way the other three arguments proceed as well.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e743">
              To the first against the second conclusion, 
              it is said in the first places that the consequent is not inconvenient, 
              but nevertheless is not able to be conceded 
              on account of heretics, lest they have an occasion for saying against us 
              that some divine person is finite.
              In the second place it is able to be said that the beginning may sound an imperfection, 
              but the beginning itself, therefore the consequent absolutely must not be admitted 
              but rather denied.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e762">
              To another, the consequence is denied. <name ref="#FascinusOfAsti">Facinus</name> 
              identifies the reason in the second <!-- in the second book? or in the second place --> because 
              God wishes that the second cause would act so that it will be perfected. 
              For if God alone were to produce the motion of the heavens, 
              then the created intelligence moving it would not be perfected through this motion,
              <pb ed="#L" n="27-v"/> 
              and nor would the soul be perfected through the motion of the body, 
              and thus for other things. 
              Therefore, though, assuming the second cause does not act, 
              the effect would be the same as if it did act, 
              nevertheless it is not in vain that the second cause acts.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e778">
              But, against this response, 
              it is argued, since every perfection 
              which the soul or second cause acquires through its action 
              or through its own participation, <!-- coefficere -->
              God is capable of supplying, therefore it is in vain a said before.
              There <name ref="#HugolinoOfOrvieto">Hugolinus</name> responds differently,
              saying that when the causality of the second cause 
              with respect to some effect is removed, 
              then the effect would not be put into being, 
              having supposed that God does not now wish to act differently 
              than before the subtraction of the causality of the second cause.
              The reason is because God does not merely wish to be the effector of the effect, 
              but the coeffector, which he is not able to be unless the second cause acts with him.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e808">
              To the third, the consequent is conceded in this sense, 
              that the entity or quality, which is the hatred of God, 
              God is able to cause. And with respect to the disproof, 
              <mentioned>because this act</mentioned> etc., this is denied because, 
              just as it is the case that there is vision and through this 
              nothing sees or is seen, 
              so it is the case that the quality, which is the hatred of God, 
              is and through this its subject is neither effected nor actualized.
              Whence just as the vision is not seeing, 
              likewise hatred is not hating. 
              If nevertheless the consequent were taken 
              for both, namely for the quality affecting and actualizing the subject, 
              then the consequence and the consequent would be denied, 
              and it would be said that, whatever is there of the entity, 
              God himself alone would be able to produce. 
              But he would not be able to affect through this 
              because this is not properly to effect something, 
              but rather to defect something
              <cit>
                <ref>according to <name ref="#Augustine">Augustinum</name></ref>
                <bibl>Augustine, XXX.</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e833">
              To the first against the third conclusion, 
              the major premise is denied, 
              just as this proposition <mentioned>every lion or every man is risible</mentioned> is denied. 
              And if such propositions were proved through the induction of their singulars by saying thus, 
              <mentioned>this lion and or this man is risible</mentioned>, and 
              <mentioned>this lion or this man is risible</mentioned>, and so on about individuals, 
              it is said that this induction is not sufficient 
              because one is not able to have enough individuals. <!-- is enough ok for "plures"; "many singulars" makes less sense -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e846">
              To the second, the consequence is denied because it is not sufficient.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e850">
              To the third, having dismissed various modes of solving these syllogisms, 
              for now I say that such things are not rightly regulated when <mentioned>speaking about everything</mentioned> 
              because such propositions are sufficiently universal, 
              though vocally they appear as universals. 
              The first part is clear because to be well regulated by 
              <mentioned>speaking about everything</mentioned> 
              requires that the major premise in the first figure 
              is sufficiently universal and really so not just vocally.
              And this is not able to be in this case because every proposition sufficiently universal 
              implies sufficiently one exclusive thing about the transposed terms. 
              And thus, if this were sufficiently universal, 
              <mentioned>every divine essence is the Father</mentioned>,
              then this consequence would be valid, 
              <mentioned>every divine essence is the Father, 
              therefore only the Father is the divine essence</mentioned>,
              which is false, therefore.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e878">
              Again, for this major premise to be sufficiently universal 
              requires that the subject suits nothing 
              that the predicate does not also suit.
              But it is not so in this case. 
              Whence it happens in the following propositions that it takes something under the subject about which 
              the predicate is not said, namely <mentioned>every divine essence is the Father</mentioned> 
              or similarly in this
              <mentioned>everything that is the Father is the Father</mentioned> 
              because the Son is the divine essence. 
              Similarly that which is the Father is predicated of the Son and the Holy Spirit 
              and nevertheless neither the Son nor the Holy Spirit is the Father. 
              Through what has been said here all the syllogisms made regarding this matter 
              are able to be solved. 
              Whence, if it is argued thus, 
              <mentioned>
                this essence is the Son, 
                this paternity is not the Son, 
                therefore this paternity is not the essence
              </mentioned>, 
              this is clear, because, if the circumlocution or the major 
              were sufficiently universal, this will be false on account of the aforesaid reasons.
            </p>
            
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-ihpfnv">
              Again, 
              <mentioned>
                this Father generates, 
                this Father is the essence, 
                therefore the essence generates
              </mentioned>. 
              It is clear that, if the major is understood as it ought, 
              it is false, and if the circumlocution does not occur, 
              then the form is not valid.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e925">
              Again, 
              <mentioned>
                every thing that is the Father is the Father, 
                everything that is the deity is that which is the Father, 
                therefore everything that is the deity is the Father
              </mentioned>.
              Such forms are easily solved through what has been said 
              because, just as they are no sufficiently regulated, 
              so the premisses are not sufficiently universal or, 
              according to another way of speaking, 
              there is not the proper circumlocution in the premises, 
              therefore the forms are not valid.
            </p>
            
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e935">
              <pb ed="#L" n="28-r"/>
              To the fourth it is said that consequent of the conversion 
              is able to be take in two ways.
              In one mode 
              <mentioned>the divine essence is generating</mentioned>,
              that is, 
              <mentioned>this which generates</mentioned>, 
              and thus it is conceded. 
              In another mode thus 
              <mentioned>the divine essence is generating</mentioned>, 
              id est, 
              <mentioned>it generates</mentioned>,
              thus the consequences is denied because 
              it is not able to be converted in this mode, 
              but only in the first mode.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e949">
              To the fifth, 
              it is said that the assumed is true with respect 
              to essential predications, but not to notional predications 
              because now there is an opposition of relations, 
              and then there would be nothing.</p>
            
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e957">
              To the sixth, the antecedent is denied 
              because it is not generating, and to the proof 
              because whatever is in the divine essence 
              is said because it out to be understood thus, 
              whatever is in the divine essence 
              either is generating, that is, either is that which is generating, 
              or that which is generated, etc.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e965">
              To the first against this corollary, 
              it is said that, if these terms 
              <mentioned>producing</mentioned> and <mentioned>produced</mentioned> 
              are understood in this way, then the major premise is false. 
              But if the terms are taken for the privation and introduced form, 
              then the minor is false 
              because the Son never had the term,
              since he is eternal.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e982">
              To the second, 
              it is said that the major premise has truth 
              in mixed compositional potencies, 
              but not in a being lacking composition and possibility,
              as in the case of the divine.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e989">
              To the third, 
              it is said that the word <mentioned>a</mentioned>
              denotes the circumstance of the substantial origin 
              or the consubstantiality of some principle with its product. 
              But the argument also speaks of a consubstantiality which notes some distinction, 
              and then the argument does not conclude because, though Maximus considered that the Father generated the Son, 
              nevertheless he would not allows that the Son was consubstantial with the Father.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q6-edpsds">
              From what has been said it is clear that 
              the antecedent of the third argument in the opposition 
              should be denied. 
              Nothing more is required, 
              what has been said is sufficient.
            </p> 
          </div>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="pg-b1q6-Dd1e4268">
          <head xml:id="pg-b1q6-Hd1e4270"><supplied>Conclusions</supplied></head>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e1009">
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q6-Qd1e4278" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d5c1-d1e3476">Post haec quaeritur</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d5c1-d1e3476">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 5, c. 1 (I, 80, ll. 26-27).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>.
            This distinction contains nine conclusions.
            The first: that the Father did not generate the divine essence, 
            nor did the divine essence generate the Son, 
            nor did the essence generate the essence.
            And <name ref="#Lombard">the Master</name> understands 
            by the name <mentioned>essence</mentioned> the divine nature, \
            which is common in three.
          </p>
          
          <p xml:id="pgb1q6-scqqdt">
            Second conclusion: that if the Father generated the divine essence, 
            the divine essence would be said relatively to the Father.
            But what is said relatively does not indicate the essence or substance, 
            as is the case, namely in the ratio of the essence, as 
            is shown through 
            <cit>
              <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Blessed Augustine</name> V <title ref="#deTrinitate">De Trinitate</title></ref>
              <bibl>Augustine, De Trinitate, V (XXX)</bibl>
            </cit>.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e1035">
            The third conclusion: 
            that if the Father generated the divine essence, 
            since the Father is the divine essence, 
            he would be the generator of the same thing that is his very self, 
            and thus the same thing would generate itself, which Augustine denies.
            <cit>
              <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name></ref>
              <bibl>Augustine, XXX</bibl>
            </cit>
            denies.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e1045">
            <!-- I've been using "generate" for gignere. "Beget" might be better in all instances -->
            The fourth conclusion: 
            since the Father is the divine essence and God, 
            if he generated the divine essence, then by virtue of that fact 
            the Father and God would be either the same thing that it generated, 
            and thus would be generated by a generating cause, as it would be, 
            which is false. 
            Similarly, the Father is not wise with the wisdom that he generates, 
            since were he to be same thing as his knowing, 
            it would follows that the Son which is this wisdom 
            generated by the Father, would be the cause of why the Father is and why wisdom, 
            against Augustine as said above. 
            <cit>
              <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Augustinum</name> ubi supra</ref>
              <bibl>Augustine, XXX</bibl>
            </cit>.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e1060">
            The fifth conclusion:
            The Father begets that which is the same as himself,
            namely the Son, who is that which the Father is 
            because what the Father is, the Son is, 
            but the Son is not who the Father is since the masculine 
            type refers to a person, 
            but the term of the neuter type indicates the substance or essence. 
          </p> 
          <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e1070">
            Sixth conclusion: when it is said 
            <mentioned>the essence is born from the essence</mentioned> 
            vel 
            <mentioned>essence is from the essence</mentioned> 
            and similar things, 
            one should understand that the Son, 
            who is the divine essence, 
            is from the Father and is born from the Father, 
            who is the divine essence. 
            Similarly, if it were to be read that  
            the substance of God beget the Son who is the same substance, 
            it should be understood that the Father beget the Son 
            who is the same substance or of the same substance with the Father
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e1082">
            Seventh conclusion: 
            that the Son and the Holy Spirit are not said to be from nothing, 
            but from something, nevertheless they are not from some material, 
            but the Son is said to be from the substance of the Father 
            because he is of the same substance with him, 
            and the Holy Spirit is said to be of the substance of the Father and the Son
            because he proceeds from both of them, 
            such that he is of the same substance.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q6-d1e1092">
            Eight conclusion: 
            that the only begotten one of God alone is said to be the Son by nature 
            because he is of the same nature and is the same nature as the Father.
            And this is sufficient for the present lecture. 
            Distinction 6 follows.
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>  
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>