<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Lecture 9</title>
        <author>Peter Gracilis</author>
        <editor>Jeffrey C. Witt</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Lecture 9</title>
          <date when="2017-10-10">October 10, 2017</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 License</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="L" n="lon">London, British Museum Royal 10 A I</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-critical-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 
          guidelines for a critical edition.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2015-11-20" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>File Started for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#L" n="33-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="pg-b1q9">
        <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e95">Lecture 9</head>
        <div xml:id="pg-b1q9-Dd1e98">
          <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e100">Concerning the text</head>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e83">
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e107" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c1-d1e3476">Nunc de veritate sive proprietate</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c1-d1e3476">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 8, c. 1 (I, 95, ll. 4).</ref></bibl>
            </cit> 
            etc. 
            This is distinction 8. 
            To the preceding it is continued thus 
            because after the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> showed 
            that in the divine there is true generation, 
            now in this distinction he puts a multitude of properties 
            signifying its perfection.
            Et this is divided into three parts 
            because in the first place the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> 
            makes determinations about the eternal being of God, 
            in the second place about his unchangeability, 
            in the third place about his simplicity. 
            The second begins at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e134" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c2-d1e3477"><sic>deus <!-- actual Lombard text has "dei" --></sic> in solius essentia</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c2-d1e3477">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 8, c. 2 (I, 97, ll.2).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>,
            the third at
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e149" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c3-d1e3475">eademque</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c3-d1e3475">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 8, c. 3 (I, 98, ll. 20).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>. 
            The first is in three parts, 
            for in the first place he shows how this name <mentioned>being</mentioned> or <mentioned>essence</mentioned> 
            is proper to God, 
            in the second place from what has been said 
            is introduces a doubt, 
            and in the third place he responds to it. 
            The second begins at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e167" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c1-d1e3533">hic diligenter</quote>
              <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c1-d1e3533">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 8, c. 1 (I, 95, ll. 21-22).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>.
            The third begins at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e177" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c1-d1e3586">illud ergo quod</quote>
              <bibl><ref type="commentary" target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c1-d1e3586">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 8, c. 1 (I, 96, ll. 20).</ref></bibl>
            </cit>.
            The second principal part is undivided, 
            but the third is divided into two parts
            because in the first place 
            the <name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> shows the simplicity of the divine nature 
            through comparison and external relations, 
            in the second place through internal relation. 
            The second begins at 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e197" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c5-d1e3477">hic diligenter</quote>
              <bibl>
                <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c5-d1e3477">Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 8, c. 5 (XXX).</ref></bibl>
              </bibl>
            </cit>.
            And this is the division of the present distinction.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="pg-b1q9-Dd1e222">
          <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e224">Question</head>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e143">
            Whether the first cause of a producibile being alone is simple,
            necessary, 
            and unchangeable or invariable?
          </p>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q9-Dd1e240">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e242">Rationes principales</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-qnasne">
              That not, there is some creature that is indivisibly simple, 
              therefore etc. 
              The antecedent is proved then because 
              to every specific grade of some thing 
              there corresponds a punctual or indivisible being. 
              This is clear because, whenever something grade is added or subtracted 
              no matter how small, the thing does not remain in the same species,
              therefore such a thing is indivisible.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-sacsne">
              <pb ed="#L" n="33-v"/>
              In the second place, 
              there something below the first cause that is necessary, 
              therefore. 
              The antecedent is clear because through
              <ref>
                <name ref="#Aquinas">the Holy Doctor</name> 
                <title ref="#SummaContraGentiles">Contra Gentiles</title>, 
                book two, chapter 29
              </ref>,
              where from what has been said 
              <cit>
                <quote>
                  therefore that in which there is not matter, 
                  or, if there is, there is not potentaility for another form, 
                  does not have the potency for non being, 
                  therefore such things are absolutely necessary
                </quote>
                <bibl>Aquinas, <title>Summa contra gentiles</title>, II, c. 29 (13, 335).</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              But it is certain that an neither an angel nor a a soul has matter, 
              therefore.
              This is confirmed 
              because an angel and a soul do not have within them 
              a principle leading them to non being, 
              therefore they have no potency for non being, 
              therefore they are necessary.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e217">
              In the third place,
              in the first cause there is an absolute modal distinction 
              and a conceptual or virtual distinction, 
              therefore.
              The antecedent for the first part is from 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#JamesViterbo">James of Viterbo</name></ref>
                <bibl>Iacobus de Viterbo, XXX</bibl>
              </cit> 
              and for the second part is from
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#AlphonsusVargas">Alphonsus</name>, distinction eight of book one, article two, conclusion four</ref>
                <bibl>Alphonsus Toletanus Vargas, I, d. 8, a. 1, conc. 4</bibl>
              </cit>.
              The consequences is clear because any such distinction is repugnant to the highest simplicity.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e235">
              In opposition is the opinion of the 
              <cit>
                <ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pl-l1d8c3"><!-- http://scta.info/resource/pl-l1d8c6" should be added when build script is capable of tokenizing these --><name ref="#Lombard">Master</name> in this distinction</ref>
                <bibl><ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pl-l1d8c3">Lombardus, Sent. I, d.8, c. 3 (I, 98)</ref> et <ref target="http://scta.info/resource/pl-l1d8c6">6, (I, 100).</ref></bibl>
              </cit>.
              Again the
              <ref>
                <name ref="#Paul">Apostle</name> in <title ref="#Itim">I Timothy</title> 6
              </ref> 
              says says that
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e318" source="http://scta.info/resource/Itim6_16">
                  God alone has immortality</quote>
                <bibl>I Timotheum 6:16</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              Again <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> III <title ref="#deTrinitate">De Trinitate</title></ref> 
              says
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e334" source="http://scta.info/resource/adt-l3">
                  God alone does not change and is not able to change</quote>
                <bibl>Augustinus, De Trinitate, III, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q9-Dd1e343">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e345">First conclusion</head> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e273">
              The first conclusion: 
              it is as necessary that the first cause is 
              as it is that a creature is able to be.
              This is proved because 
              inasmuch as it is necessary that God is God and is omnipotent, 
              by as much necessity he is externally productive, 
              and by as much necessity is something external able to be produced 
              and is able to have being, 
              therefore etc.
              This is confirmed because, 
              if the first cause were not able to produce anything outside itself, 
              it would seem that from the fact that something is producible it would be produced, 
              but this is impossible. 
              Nor does this seem to be a problem 
              because it would still be able to corrupt this whole 
              and then recreate it, 
              therefore.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e322">
              First corollary: 
              thought it is not the case that a creature is not able not to be, 
              nevertheless if the first cause 
              were to act outside itself through the mode of nature, 
              then it would be necessary for some producible thing to be.
              The first part is clear 
              because some created thing is contingently produced by 
              and in conserved in its being. 
              The second part is clear 
              because, 
              if one thing were produced and not another thing, 
              then either this would be because 
              it would were determined that this thing be produced
              and not the other, 
              and not this because this is to produce freely 
              since one is equally as possible as the other,
              or this would be because one thing would be able to be produced and not the other, 
              but this is not the case because then it would be producible and not producibile. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e345">
              Second corollary: 
              if the first cause were to act outside itself 
              necessarily and naturally, all producibile and corruptibile things 
              would be produced and corrupted at the same time and equally. 
              This is clear because if <c>a</c> fire itself were able to 
              produce <c>b</c> heat and corrupt <c>b</c> heat, 
              it would produce and corrupt at the same time. 
              Therefore, 
              since the first cause alone is able with another <!-- need translation help here -->
              it is able in the genus of an efficient cause, 
              the proposed follows that if it were to act naturally, etc.
              
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e370">
              Third corollary: 
              it is not stand that the first cause is productive 
              of every producible creature 
              and to this to act outside of itself from the necessity of nature. 
              This is clear to this that to produce naturally, 
              it would follows that all producible things are produced and corrupted at the same time and equally. 
              But this implies a contradiction, therefore. 
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q9-Dd1e377">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e379">Second conclusion</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e378">
              The second conclusion: though only three supposites 
              are distinguished in the one super simple essence, 
              nevertheless this is not properly called diversity or difference.
              The first part is clear through faith because
              there is one Father, another Son, and another Holy Spirit, 
              therefore only three supposites are distinguished in the divine essence. 
              This is confirmed 
              because a distinction or difference is nothing, 
              therefore the should not be put in God. 
              This is clear because whatever is in God is something. 
              The antecedent is clear 
              because if only God and man were to exists and nothing else, 
              God and man would still be different, 
              therefore distinction or difference are nothing something or somethings. 
              For this  
              <pb ed="#L" n="34-r"/>
              conclusion there is the reasoning 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> VI <title ref="#deTrinitate">De Trinitate</title>, chapter 4, de magnis<!-- translation--></ref>
                <bibl>Augustinus, De Trinitate, VI, c. 4</bibl>
              </cit> 
              and 
              <cit> <!-- could this be the same ref ?? -->
                <ref>chapter 14, de parvis <!-- translation ?? --></ref>
                <bibl>Augustinus, De Trinitate, VI, c. 14</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              From the second part of the conclusion, 
              it follows that though it would be said truly and properly 
              that some things are distinguished in reality, 
              and in intention, and in reason, 
              nevertheless it is not properly said that 
              this distinct is intentional, real, or of reason. 
              This is clear 
              because a distinction is nothing, 
              therefore it is not. 
              The consequence is clear 
              because what is absolutely nothing does not exists
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e425">
              First corollary: 
              every perfection 
              which God really is some perfection of God formally. 
              This is clear because, 
              if the divine perfections 
              in some mode differed or were different, 
              it would follow that the divine supposites 
              would not differ only in the divine essence.
              The consequence is clear in 
              <cit>
                <ref>the first part of the second conclusion</ref>
                <bibl>Vide supra</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e435">
              Second corollary: 
              that just among divine perfections 
              there is no formal distinction, 
              so also are a distinction of reason or modal distinction repugnant to them 
              Or thus, 
              just as it does not stand that 
              the divine perfections are distinguished formally, 
              so it is also repugnant for them 
              to be distinguished by reason or formally. 
              This is clear because 
              otherwise in them there 
              would not be the highest simplicity and indifference.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e447">
              Third corollary: 
              just as it is repugnant that there are a plurality of Gods, 
              so it is repugnant that there are a formal diversity of perfections in God. 
              This is clear because, 
              if such a plurality of formalities in God were possible, 
              it follows that there is something which is absolutely formally God which is not every God. 
              Again, it would follow that something would be 
              God really which is merely contingent, 
              but this is as repugnant as it is that there are many gods, 
              therefore. 
              The first consequence is proved 
              because if divine justice is God formally, 
              then the divine wisdom, 
              if it is formally not justice, 
              then it will not be God formally. 
              The second consequence is clear 
              because the fact that <mentioned>God wants to beatify 
              <name ref="#Peter">Peter</name></mentioned> is really God, 
              and nevertheless by positing formalities of this type 
              God is contingently.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-itcpci">
              These three corollaries seem to be from the mind of 
              <ref><name ref="#Anselm">Anselm</name>  in the <title ref="#Monologion">Monologion</title> chapter 17</ref> 
              who says 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e480">
                  whatever is said essentially about the highest essence, 
                  thus this is in one consideration essentially one. 
                  For since some man is said to be a body, rational, and man, 
                  he is not in any mode or consideration said to be three things. 
                  Thus truly the highest divine essence is in no way said in such a way that 
                  it is not this same thing according to consideration and according to another</quote>
                <bibl>Anselmus, Monologion, 17, (I, 31, ll. 25-32)</bibl>
              </cit>.
              From this these corollary seem to be clear.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q9-Dd1e494">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e496">Third conclusion</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e511">
              Third conclusion: just as the first cause alone 
              has every perfection absolutely and is including itself, 
              so also is it formally and completely lacking any kind of compositions 
              and excluding from itself. <!-- translation help needed -->
              The first part is proved because according to <name ref="#Anselm">Anselm</name> God is 
              
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e506">that which nothing greater or better is able to be thought</quote>
                <bibl>Anselmus, Proslogion 3 (I, 103, ll. 1-2)</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              The second part is because simplicity should be placed before composition
              according to 
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> <title ref="#DeQuantitateAnimae">De quantitate animae</title>, chapter 12</ref>
                <bibl>Augustinus, De quantitate, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>,
              ergo, 
              But the first cause alone is of the highest simplicity. 
              This is clear indivisibility, immutability, and per se actuality 
              belong to the ratio of simplicity, 
              but these things suit God alone 
              and are not able to be found in a creature.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e539">
              The first corollary: 
              any species either of a given or giveable form are perfectly 
              confluibile <!-- translation help --> into a superior form or species. 
              This is clear because no such species is unchangeable in its being, 
              therefore God is able to make it that flow together in a unified way into something superior.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e549">
              The second corollary: 
              it is not the case that some individual depends on a first cause 
              and unitively contains every degree of perfection.
              This is clear because 
              then such an individual would not be able flow unitively 
              with another individual into a superior species 
              or into some more perfect individual. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e572">
              The third corollary: 
              it is not the case for some individual that it is repugnant that 
              some dependent created being is not able to be subjectively under some accident 
              and that it is repugnant that this created thing truly is able 
              to unitively contain every grade of simplicity. <!-- NEED TRANSLATION HELP -->
              This is clear because non individual of any given 
              <pb ed="#L" n="34v"/>
              or giveable species is able to be so simple 
              that it is not able to be the subject of an elicited act or 
              the subject of some habit infused by God, therefore. 
              The antecedent is clear because simplicity of this type suits God alone.
              From what has been said the affirmative part of the conclusion follows.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q9-Dd1e561">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e563">Objections</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e600">
              Against the first conclusion and its corollaries: 
              something other than God is necessary, therefore. 
              The antecedent is proved because the divine perfection goes out to what is produced similar to itself 
              to the degree that is not repugnant to the creature. 
              But to be necessary is not repugnant to a creature, 
              therefore the divine goodness produces the creatures in this way. 
              The major premise is known. 
              The minor premise is clear because,
              if it were repugnant to the creature to be necessary, 
              then it would seem to be by virtue of the fact that it comes from another. 
              But this is not the case 
              because the Son has his being from another, 
              and nevertheless it does not have this being contingently, 
              therefore.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e632">
              In the second place, 
              if an angel or the soul were able not to be, 
              then this would be because God withdrew his influence from them.
              But this is impossible 
              because this would mean his goodness had changed, 
              therefore such things are not able to be. 
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e646">
              In the third place: 
              substances separated from matter 
              do not have a passive potency for privation or corruption, 
              therefore they are not able not to be. 
              The consequence holds 
              since matter is the ratio of maintenance and corruption in creatures. 
              These are the arguments of <name ref="#Aquinas">the Holy Doctor</name>,
              in the place it was noted earlier at the beginning of the question.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e665">
              In the fourth place: 
              because either for something to be necessary it corresponds 
              precisely either that it is punctual or quantitive.
              If the first, then it is not of immense perfection. 
              If the second, 
              then it is able to be imagined in this species 
              that there is a greater and lesser necessity,  
              since for every thing that has quantity 
              there is able to be given something less,  
              so it is possible to give to this necessity a lesser quantity, 
              and thus there will be many types of necessity.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e706">
              In the fifth place: 
              if the entire line of producbile things were contingent with respect to being and non being, 
              it follows that the whole would be able to be put completely into being. 
              The consequent is false through what has been said 
              because the first cause would not be able to act outside itself. 
              The consequence is clear 
              because the whole is able not to be as
              <cit>
                <ref>the first corollary</ref>
                <bibl>Vide supra</bibl>
              </cit> 
              says.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e715">
              In the sixth place: 
              no individual of an inferior species 
              is able to contain the total perfection of its species, 
              therefore it is necessary that one thing is not able to contain the total breadth of necessity, 
              therefore there is not only one thing in that species.
              The antecedent is clear through the
              <cit>
                <ref>second corollary of the third conclusion</ref>
                <bibl>Vide supra</bibl>
              </cit>, 
              and the consequences are clear.
              This is confirmed 
              because <mentioned>to be</mentioned>, as the proposition
              <mentioned>man is an animal</mentioned> signified, 
              is necessary being, 
              therefore there are many necessary beings. 
              The consequence holds because this is not God..
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e756">
              Again, to this proposition nothing is, 
              a contradiction does not follow, 
              there this is able to be true, 
              therefore nothing is necessary to be necessary. 
              The consequences holds, 
              and the antecedent is proved 
              because to no negative does an affirmative follow, 
              therefore neither does some contradiction 
              because every contradiction 
              is composed from an affirmative and negative 
              or at least includes one.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e791">
              Against the second conclusion: 
              in the first place it is argued 
              the authority the <ref><name ref="#JohnDamascenus">Damascene</name>, in book one, chapter three</ref>,
              where he says 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e627">
                  Whatever we say about God affirmatively 
                  does not show his nature but those things, 
                  which are about his nature. For if you say he is good, 
                  if just, and if wise, and anything else, you do not speak his nature.
                </quote>
                <bibl>Ioannes Damescenus, I, c. 4, (PG 94.799BC); Burgundionis versio 4,5, p. 21, 41-45)</bibl> <!-- quote also in Marsilius of Inghen, q. 12, p. 83,  and Rimini 1, d. 8, q. 1, p. 25-->
              </cit>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e806">
              Against the first corollary: 
              if God were immensely simple, 
              he would be so either divisibly or indivisibly. 
              Not the first because then he would have parts. 
              Not the second because then he alone through his indivisibility would stand apart from nothing, 
              and thus the divine essence would be infinitely less distant from an angel than any creature, 
              which is false.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e816">
              In the second place, 
              wisdom in common is not justice in common, 
              therefore infinite wisdom is not infinite justice. 
              The consequence holds because 
              infinity does not destroy the proper ratio of something, 
              as it seems.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e825">
              Against the second corollary: 
              those things which are not synonymous 
              signify diverse things or the same thing by diverse reasons. 
              But goodness, and justice, mercy, and eternity are not synonymous in God, therefore. 
              But they do not 
              <pb ed="#L" n="35-r"/> 
              signify diverse things, therefore 
              by diverse modes. 
              Therefore in God there is a modal distinction as stated by  
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#JamesViterbo">James of Viterbo</name>, <title>Quodlibet</title> three, question seven</ref>
                <bibl>Iacobus de Viterbio, Quodlibet III, q. 7, 2, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-ssqnmv">
              In the second place it follows that
              willing divine would be formally and an intellective divine 
              and the conversely. 
              The consequent is false 
              because then, whatever the object may be, 
              one would be the object of the other. 
              This mode is false
              because God understands the evil of guilt 
              which he nevertheless in no way wishes.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e849">
              Third: that which 
              necessitates the intellect to essentially distinct acts 
              is distinguished according to reason or conceptually. 
              But the divine perfections necessitate 
              the intellect to essentially distinct acts, 
              therefore divine perfections of this type 
              are distinct conceptually or virtually. 
              The major is clear where one thing necessitates 
              to essentially distinct acts this makes the same thing 
              that really distinct diverse things would make.
              The minor is clear because divine wisdom necessitates the intellect 
              to the concept of wisdom and goodness to the concept of goodness, 
              and such concepts are really and essential distinct, 
              therefore, ergo. <name ref="#AlphonsusVargas">Alphonsus</name>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e892">
              In the fourth place against the third corollary: 
              non justice is not repugnant to wisdom as such, 
              therefore wisdom in some mode is the same as justice. 
              But another god is not repugnant to divine wisdom, 
              therefore. <!-- needs translation review -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e901">
              Against the third conclusion 
              is another proposition in <title ref="#deCausis">De causis</title> 
              in which it is said that <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qiesqnd">intelligence is a substance 
              which is not divided</quote>, 
              therefore it is not the case that God alone is undivided.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-pdaiei">
              In the second place the
              <ref><name ref="#Aristotle">Philosohper</name> II <title ref="#deAnima">De anima</title></ref>
              says 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e4530">the intellect absolutely unmixed and immaterial</quote>
                <bibl>Aristoteles, De anima, II, XXX</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e918">
              In the third place, 
              against the first corollary 
              is the first reasons in the opposition 
              because some simple thing is so 
              simple that only a single grade and punctual being corresponds to it, 
              therefore.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e930">
              In the fourth place, 
              by the authority of the 
              <ref>
                <name ref="#Averroes">Commentator</name> 
                in book 12 of the <title ref="#Metaphysics">Metaphysics</title>
              </ref> 
              who says that  
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qd1e724">all forms 
                  are existing in actuality in the first mover 
                  which are in potency in the prime matter</quote>
                <bibl>
                  <name>Averroes</name>, 
                  XII 
                  <title>Comment. in Metaphysica</title>, 
                  commento 18. 
                  (Juntina VIII <!-- second edition -->, 305v I)
                </bibl>
              </cit>,
              therefore is not in God simplicity in every form. 
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="pg-b1q9-Dd1e1033">
            <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e1035">Responses</head>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e949">
              To the first, 
              the antecedent is denied. 
              To the proof, 
              the major and minor is denied. 
              And to the proof of the minor, 
              I say that to be necessary is repugnant to the creature 
              not only from that which is from another, 
              but also because it is freely contingently produced from nothing 
              and contingently conserved.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e957">
              To the second, the assumed is conceded 
              and it is denied that it is impossible 
              because it does not follow that the divine will changes or is changeable.
              Otherwise it would be able to be proved 
              that ever future thing comes about necessarily.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e972">
              To the third, 
              the consequence is denied 
              because then the accidents and 
              the light produced in some manner 
              in medium would not be able not to be. 
              In the second place, 
              I say that though they do not have matter, 
              nevertheless they have their own nothingness 
              as if matter and this suffices.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e981">
              To the fourth, 
              it is able to be said that punctual and indivisible being corresponds to it, 
              and the consequence is denied, 
              therefore it is not of immense perfection 
              because at the same time it is indivisible, super simple, and immense, not having 
              in itself formally any gradual latitude although it contains 
              supereminently every latitude of perfection.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e999">
              To the fifth, 
              the consequent is conceded 
              because some part of the latitude is able to be put into being, 
              and if it is inferred, 
              then it is able to be put into being at the same time.
              The consequence is denied 
              because, just as it also does not follow 
              that some part of that latitude is able to be put into being, 
              therefore it is possible that some part of it be put into being, 
              so it does not follow that some continuous part <c>a</c> from Socrates is able to be seen, 
              therefore Socrates is able to see some continuous part <c>a</c>. 
              Nor does it follow that some possible grade of perfection is able to be put into being, 
              therefore it is possible that some possible grade of perfection should be put into being, 
              thought I hold the consequent to be probable 
              in 
              <cit>
                <ref>my principio</ref>
                <bibl>Supra vide</bibl>
              </cit> 
              against what it said before.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1027">
              To the sixth, 
              the consequence is denied 
              because the deity does not exist in manner of a created person 
              nor that of the divine person through the mode of individuals 
              because, 
              thought two human beings are some one thing which is greater than one alone, 
              nevertheless two divine persons 
              are not greater than one alone, as  
              <cit>
                <ref><name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> says in VIII <title ref="#deTrinitate">De Trinitate</title>, capitulo primo</ref>
                <bibl>Augustinus, De Trinitate, VIII, c. 1 (XXX)</bibl>
              </cit>.
            </p> 
            
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1045">
              To another, 
              the consequence is denied 
              because the conclusion and corollary are understood about real entities 
              and not about things 
              <pb ed="#L" n="35-v"/>  
              signifying in a complex way.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-aanesa">
              To another, 
              the antecedent is denied 
              because for this, it follows 
              that to be necessary is not to be necessary. 
              And to the disproof, 
              I say that for the impossible, 
              something follows, 
              and as a consequence 
              the from the negative, 
              the affirmative follows.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-apcesa">
              To the first against the second conclusion,
              it is said that <name ref="#JohnDamascenus">Damascenus</name>
              does not speak about perfections that are not really in God, 
              but about names which are predicated of God, 
              some of which according to him are not predicated of his nature, 
              but about those things which are concerning his nature 
              which should not be understood with respect to the thing signified 
              because, 
              if a thing which is divine wisdom were not the divine nature, 
              but something concerning his nature, 
              it would not only be distinguished formally, 
              but really and absolutely, 
              which is false. 
              But it is understood with respect to the mode of predicating 
              because such names are predicated of God denominatively. 
              And those things that are predicated about God with respect to 
              the mode of predicated of God with respect to the mode of predicating
              do not speak about nature about, 
              but about something concerning nature. 
              This is the solution of <name ref="#AlphonsusVargas">Alphonsus</name>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1101">
              To the second, 
              in the first place it would be able to be said that divisibly 
              or through a divisible he distances himself from an angel 
              because he distances himself through the total perfection of all creaturea 
              actual and possible. 
              And the consequences is denied, 
              therefore so are parts 
              because this divisibility is not instrinsic in God, but extrinsic.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1110">
              In the second place, 
              by denying the consequence 
              it would be able to be said that 
              he distances himself indivisibly, 
              therefore infinitely less than anything below 
              because that which is indivisible through 
              what it distances itself is immense 
              because it is God.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1118">
              To another, 
              the consequence is denied.
              The reason is because infinite wisdom 
              and infinite goodness in reality 
              are something circumscribed by every reasons of the intellect. 
              But wisdom in general and goodness in general 
              are not thus because they are not
              unless some concept or being of reason. 
              And to the proof, 
              it is conceded 
              because infinity does not destroy the formal reason of something, 
              but this does not prove the intent 
              because wisdom and goodness in general 
              are not only predicated of infinite wisdom and goodness, 
              but also of finite wisdom and goodness. 
              About this see <name ref="#AlphonsusVargas">Alphonsum</name>.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1143">
              To another against the third corollary, 
              having conceded the antecedent, 
              the consequence is denied,
              for it does not follow that 
              this thing is in diverse ways 
              because it is possible that 
              the proposed same signified thing is 
              in one true and another false, 
              nevertheless it does not follow 
              that the thing signified is true and false.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1151">
              To another, 
              the consequent is conceded. 
              And to the proof, <mentioned>because the object of one</mentioned>, etc., 
              it is conceded.
              And when it is disproved,
              <mentioned>because God understand evil</mentioned> etc., 
              it is conceded, 
              but what is inferred does not follow.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1160">
              In the second place I say that the divine will understands 
              every evil because the divine intellect 
              which understands is formally the divine will. 
              Evil therefore is an object of the will, 
              not as something willed, 
              but as something known and understood.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1168">
              In the third place 
              this consequence would be able to be denied, 
              the divine will and intellect are the same, 
              therefore whatever the intellect understands, 
              the will wills.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1174">
              To another, 
              the major is denied and the minor 
              because it is not necessary that everything that
              necessitates to distinct concepts is conceptually distinct 
              unless we wish from the use of a word. <!-- translation help -->
              Nor also does divine perfection necessitate 
              to the distinction of diverse acts as the argument assumes.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1195">
              To the argument 
              against the third corollary, 
              the major is denied because divine wisdom 
              is every perfection formally, 
              and everything that is <sic>is</sic> better than 
              what is absolutely not under the good intellect. <!-- need translation help -->
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1203">
              To the first authority against the 
              the third conclusion, 
              intelligence is a substance which is not divided. 
              This is true with respect to parts of nature 
              with respect to duration, 
              which is a whole at one and the same time.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1211">
              To another, 
              it is said that the intellectu is a simple power, 
              that is, non organic. 
              This is the position of the <name ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name>. 
              In the second place it is said that 
              simple in some mode is not simple absolutely 
              because every creature in some mode is a composite 
              subject to potentiality.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1225">
              To the first reason in the opposition, 
              it is said that, if the antecedent 
              is understood about simplicity absolutely, 
              then it is false.
              And to the proof, 
              it is said that consequence is not valid. 
              And if it were further inferred 
              that the soul is not simple, 
              therefore it has parts, 
              the consequence is denied.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1233">
              To another, it is said that forms of this type 
              are in the first mover are indistinct 
              in act because the creature in God is not other than the divine nature
              <pb ed="#L" n="36-r"/>
              indistinct within.
            </p> 
            <p xml:id="pgb1q9-aarspd">
              To the other arguements in the opposition, 
              the solution is clear through what has been said.
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="pg-b1q9-Dd1e884">
          <head xml:id="pg-b1q9-Hd1e886">
            <supplied>Conclusions for distinction eight</supplied>
          </head>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1250">
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="pg-b1q9-Qndvvsp" source="http://scta.info/resource/pll1d8c1-d1e3476">Nunc de veritate seu proprietate</quote>
              <bibl>Lombardus, Sent. I, d. 8, c. 1 (I, 95, ll. 4).</bibl>
            </cit>. 
            This distinction contains nine conclusions. 
            First that God alone truly and properly is
            because his essence did not know past or future, 
            that is not under any past or future, 
            as other created things are.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1264">
            Second conclusion: 
            therefore he says God always was and always will be, 
            so that it is understood that he did not begin to be 
            nor will he cease to be. 
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1270">
            Third conclusion: 
            that though substantive words 
            about diverse times are said about God, 
            namely that he has been, will be, is and was, 
            nevertheless they are not said about God 
            because the that the divine being is subjected to 
            to the past or the future with temporal motion 
            is repugnant to God, 
            but they are said for the purpose of denoting 
            that God is eternity and the property of his
            permanence.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1286">
            Fourth conclusion: 
            the essence of God alone is properly said to be incommutable 
            because it does not change and is not able to change. 
            However every creature is able to be changed, 
            but God is not neither in space nor in time nor in affection, 
            and thus he created all creatures without any change in himself.
            And as a consequence, God alone properly has immortality. 
            However every creature is mortal from its nature 
            because its mutation is called death.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1299">
            Fifth conclusion: 
            God alone is truly or properly simple
            because in him there is not a diversity or different mode or multitude 
            of parts or accidents or forms
            Ever creature is multiple, 
            although a spiritual creature with respect to what is corporeal 
            is said to be simple, 
            nevertheless not truly simple 
            because in such a thing there is a diversity of accidents or accidental forms, 
            as there are in animals, humans, and angels, 
            for nothing that is truly simple is changeable. 
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1311">
            Sixth conclusion: that 
            the soul with respect to the body is said to be simple 
            because the parts<!-- molae greek word for parts?? --> are not spread 
            through the space of place, 
            but in each body the whole is all together 
            and in each of its parts.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1318">
            Seventh conclusion: 
            that though God is said in many ways, 
            namely good, just, wise, and great, 
            nevertheless this is not on account of a diversity of accidents, 
            but on account of a multitude of names which, 
            though they are many and diverse, 
            nevertheless they signify one thing, 
            namely the divine nature.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1328">
            Eight conclusion: 
            that God is not properly called substance 
            as if he is the subject of his goodness or of some accident, 
            just as a bodily substance, 
            which is called substance 
            because it subsists 
            and is the subject of many accidents, 
            but God is properly and truly called essence.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="pgb1q9-d1e1336">
            Ninth conclusion: 
            God is therefore said to be simple 
            because he is whatever he has, 
            with the exception that a person is said relatively to another, 
            nevertheless one is not the other. 
            For the Father has the Son 
            to whom he is said relatively, 
            and nevertheless the Father is not the Son, 
            and the Son has the Father, 
            and nevertheless is not the Father 
            in whom he is truly said to himself and not to another, 
            this is what he has. <!-- translation help --> 
            Whence God himself is one and has life 
            and he is one life 
            and there is not one thing that is having 
            and another thing which is had, 
            just as in other things 
            where some distinction always follows. 
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>  
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>